<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Naturall philosophy: or A description of the vvorld, and of the severall creatures therein contained viz. of angels, of mankinde, of the heavens, the starres, the planets, the foure elements, with their order, nature and government: as also of minerals, mettals, plants, and precious stones; with their colours, formes, and vertues. By Daniel Widdovves.</title>
            <title>Rerum naturalium doctrina methodica. English. Abridgments</title>
            <author>Scribonius, Wilhelm Adolf, fl. 1576-1583.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117038</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852253</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852253</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17567</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17567)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1394:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Naturall philosophy: or A description of the vvorld, and of the severall creatures therein contained viz. of angels, of mankinde, of the heavens, the starres, the planets, the foure elements, with their order, nature and government: as also of minerals, mettals, plants, and precious stones; with their colours, formes, and vertues. By Daniel Widdovves.</title>
                  <title>Rerum naturalium doctrina methodica. English. Abridgments</title>
                  <author>Scribonius, Wilhelm Adolf, fl. 1576-1583.</author>
                  <author>Widdowes, Daniel.</author>
                  <author>Scribonius, Wilhelm Adolf, fl. 1576-1583. Rerum physicarum juxta leges logicas methodica explicatio. aut</author>
                  <author>Woodhouse, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, corrected and enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[14], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Tho. Cotes, for Iohn Bellamie, and are to be sold at the three Golden Lyons in Cornehill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation and abridgment, by Daniel Widdowes or Woodhouse, of "Rerum naturalium doctrina methodica" by Wilhelm Adolf Scribonius, which is a revision of his "Rerum physicarum juxta leges logicas methodica explicatio".</note>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: I. Wyddowes, alias Woodhouse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Naturall philosophie.</note>
                  <note>A variant (STC 22112.5) has Benjamin Allen's name as publisher in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Natural history --  Pre-Linnean works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17567:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NATVRALL PHILOSOPHY: <hi>OR</hi> A DESCRIPTION OF THE WORLD, AND OF the ſeverall Creatures therein contained: <hi>Viz.</hi> Of Angels, of Mankinde, of the Heavens, the Starres, the Planets, the foure Elements, with their order, nature and government: As alſo of Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, Mettals, Plants, and Precious ſtones; with their colours, formes, and vertues.</p>
            <p>By DANIEL WIDDOVVES.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition, corrected and enlarged.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 King. 4. 33.</bibl> 
               <hi>He ſpake of Trees, from the Cedar tree that is in Libanon, even to the Iſsope that ſpringeth out of the wall: He ſpake alſo of Beaſts, and of Fowles, and of creeping things, and of Fiſhes.</hi>
            </q>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe little leaves the Worlds huge load ſuſtaine,</l>
               <l>And what beſides the great World can containe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Tho. Cotes,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie,</hi> and are to be ſold at the three <hi>Golden Lyons</hi> in <hi>Cornehill.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17567:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE Sir <hi>William Parſons</hi> Knight Barronet, his Maieſties Survayour Generall, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>miſsioner in the Court of Wards, and one of</hi> his Maieſties moſt Honourable Privie Counſell in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe preſent to your view a ſmall frame of the world, and of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures therein contained, drawne with the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilles of iudicious <hi>Scribon,</hi> and of <hi>D. W.</hi> A worke in nature not unlike to our Survayes in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that repreſent moſt lively, vaſte Countries within a ſmall Map. I offer this to you, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heretofore given to you an account of
<pb facs="tcp:17567:3"/> thoſe ſervices that I have lately done in the ſurvey of <hi>Ireland,</hi> you being Survayor Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of that kingdome, wherein I have ſpent the moſt part of thirty yeares, in the ſervice of my Prince and Country, <hi>Tam Marte, quam Mercurio,</hi> both by Pike and Pen, with great toyle, much hazard, and many hurts; but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle profit. Notwithſtanding, your demerits and worth be ſuch, as Gratitude hath choſen your Patronage: and Devotion wiſheth all honour, health, and happineſſe to you, to my good Lady, and to yours,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your Honours Command, I. Wyddowes, <hi>alias</hi> Woodhouſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:17567:3"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <item>WHat philoſophie is. <hi>Page. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What God is. <hi>Ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The actions of God towfold. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What Angels are. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How they appeare. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What their office is. 2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of motions, qualities, colours, taſting, &amp;c.</head>
               <item>TWo kinds of movers in the world. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How created things move. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What motion is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Five things in motion. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Six kinds of motion. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What qualities are. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the qualitie of heate is. 3</item>
               <item>Lightneſſe and thinneſſe commeth of heate. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Heavineſſe and thickneſſe of cold. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What proceedeth from moyſture. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What proceedeth from dryneſſe. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The uſe of colours. 4</item>
               <item>What a Simple colour is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>White, what it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Blacke, what it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of mixt colours, and whence they proceed. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How they are compounded. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Taſting, whence it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:4"/>
               <item>The diverſe kindes of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Smelling whence it proceeds, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bad. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Qualities ariſing by meanes, what they be. 5</item>
               <item>Hid qualities how knowne. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They are either native or paſsionate. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Native governed by the Heavens. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How and when of moſt effecacie. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Paſsionate how effected. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What concord is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What diſcord is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Celeſtiall bodies, as the Heavens, the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, the Starres, with their places, order, and government.</head>
               <item>WHat Heaven is. 6</item>
               <item>What the Firmament is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the Etheriall part of it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What a Starre is, with their diverſe kinds. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their operation over bodies, and how it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their riſing and falling, and how it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Starres fixed or wandring. 7</item>
               <item>How knowne from Planets. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How and where contained in the heavens. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Starres Maſculine and Feminine. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Sagitarius, 8</item>
               <item>Capricornus, Aquarius, Piſces. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Starres in the Zodiack. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the Northerne Conſtellations are. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the Southerne Conſtellations are. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What Planets are. 9</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:4"/>
               <item>Why called wandring. 9</item>
               <item>When and how they are ſtayed. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When and how they goe backe. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The virtue and force of Planets. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The proper houſe of each Planet. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Planets, ſome of one light; ſome of more. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Coniunction of Planets common or ſpeciall. 10</item>
               <item>They preſage things to come, and how. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of Saturne, his properties, and how he ruleth in the body; and over whom. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of Iupiter, his properties, how he ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the body; and over whom. 11</item>
               <item>A deſcription of Mars, his properties, how hee ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the body, and in whom. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of the Sunne, the office and uſe of it, and how and whom it governes. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It maketh Winter and Summer, length and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of dayes. 12</item>
               <item>A deſcription of Venus, her properties, how and in whom ſhe governs. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of Mercury, his nature, how and in whom he ruleth. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A deſcription of the Moone. 13</item>
               <item>How the Moone increaſeth and decreaſeth. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When and how the Moone is in the full. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In what time ſhe endeth her revolution. 14</item>
               <item>What a Comet is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The light of ſome Planets, eſpecially of the Sun &amp; Moone, faileth ſometime, &amp; the reaſon of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the eclipſe of the Sun and Moone, &amp; the reaſon of them. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:17567:5"/>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the foure Elements.</head>
               <item>WHat Elements are. 15</item>
               <item>Some Elements cleare, as ayre &amp; water. <hi>ib</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The regions of the Ayre. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The neceſsity of the Ayre. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What water is, the natures and uſes of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why the water in the Sea is ſalt. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The reaſon of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Flouds and Fountaines. 16</item>
               <item>Diverſe colours and taſts of water. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the earth is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The compaſſe of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of concreat and mixt bodies. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of mixed liveleſſe natures, as meteors, what they be, with their ſeverall kinds, and the reaſon of them. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of mixed fiery meteors, as thunder, what it is, and the reaſon of it. 17</item>
               <item>Of lightning, what it is, and the reaſon of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of watery Meteors, as clouds, what they be, and the reaſon of them. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diverſe ſhapes in the clouds, &amp; the reaſon of it. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A falſe Sunne, how occaſioned. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A rainebow, how occaſioned. 18</item>
               <item>A deſcription of the rainebow, &amp; the ſignes of it. <hi>ib</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Meteors of diſſolved clouds, with the reaſon of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Snow what it is, and how occaſioned. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hayle what it is, and how occaſioned. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dew what it is, and how occaſioned. 19</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:5"/>
               <item>Manna, what it is. 19</item>
               <item>Froſt, what it is, and how occaſioned. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Meteors cauſed of both kinds of Smoake, the reaſon of them. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Winde what it is, and the diverſe kindes of it, as Storme, Whirlewinde, Earthquake. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of mixed living Natures.</head>
               <item>WHat a vegetative ſoule is, with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and office of it. 20</item>
               <item>What nouriſhment is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What concoction is, with the neceſsitie of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The neceſsitie of temperate heate cleared by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of good, and hurt of bad concoction. 21</item>
               <item>Whence inflammation ariſeth. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The companions of concoction are, 1. Attraction, 2. Retention, 3. Expulſion, what they are. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What generation is. 22</item>
               <item>What is the obiect of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Minerals and Mettals.</head>
               <item>BRimſtone, what it is, the nature of it. 22</item>
               <item>Quickſilver what it is, the nature of it. 23</item>
               <item>Gold what it is, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Where it is found. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Silver what it is, the difference betwixt gold and it. 24</item>
               <item>Braſſe what it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Copperaſſe what it is, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:6"/>
               <item>Iron, the nature of it. 24</item>
               <item>Lead, the nature of it. 25</item>
               <item>Tynne, what it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Stones, whereof they are, and their variety. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pretious ſtones. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cryſtall the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Adamant, the nature of it. 26</item>
               <item>Saphyr, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Smaragde, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sardonyx, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Selenites, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Carbuncle, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Calcedonian, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aſſarites, the nature of it. 27</item>
               <item>Rubie, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Topaz, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hiacinth, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Corrall, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Asbeſtos, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Loadeſtone, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Galactites, the nature of it. 28</item>
               <item>Achates, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Turcoys, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Corneolus, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chryſopraſus, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hematite, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chelidonius, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alectorius, the nature of it. 29</item>
               <item>Toadeſtone, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Crabs eye, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pearch ſtone. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Curpe ſtone, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:6"/>
               <item>Porphirite, Allabaſtar. 29</item>
               <item>Ophite. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Common ſtones. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salt, what it is, and the nature of it. 30</item>
               <item>Salt Amoniack, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salt Peter. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salt Gemme. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salt of Indie. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salt of water. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alome. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Liquid Alome. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hard Alome. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bitume. 31</item>
               <item>Liquid Bitume. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Naphtha Petreolum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ambar of Arabia. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hard Bitume <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Piſſaphaltus. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Succinum. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Terra Lemnia. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bole Armenian. 32</item>
               <item>Terra Samia. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ampelite. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chalke. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Blacke Chalke, with the nature of them all. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of natures perfectly living.</head>
               <item>WHat natures perfectly living are. 32</item>
               <item>Of Plants. 33</item>
               <item>Frankincenſe tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Myrrhe tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:7"/>
               <item>Mace, the nature of it. 33</item>
               <item>Nutmeg, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pepper, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wilde Palme tree, the nature of it. 34</item>
               <item>Balſame tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Balme, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pomegranet; the nature of it. 35</item>
               <item>Pome Citron, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Orange. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cedar; the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Figtree. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quince tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lawrell tree, the nature of it. 36</item>
               <item>Iuniper tres, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cheſnut tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beech tree, the nature of it. 37</item>
               <item>Oke tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ilex tree, the nature of it. 38</item>
               <item>Corke tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pine Appletree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pitch tree. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Firre tree. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Larix tree, the nature of it! 39</item>
               <item>Elme tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alder tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Teile tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Boxe tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Birch tree, the nature of it. 40</item>
               <item>Willow tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poplar tree, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Shrubs. 41</item>
               <item>Cinnamon, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:7"/>
               <item>Caſsia Fiſtula, the nature of it. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Haſell, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Elderne, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Barberies, the nature of it. 42</item>
               <item>Small Rayſin, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Roſe tree, the nature of it. 43</item>
               <item>Bramble, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gooſeberries, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colutea, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hearbes. 44</item>
               <item>Wheate, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Barley, the nature of it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spelte, Rye, Oates, Millet, their nature. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rize, Lintils, Peaſe; Beanes, their nature. 45</item>
               <item>Pot hearbes. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Coleworts, Spinage, Lettiſe, their nature. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beets, Purſlaine, Mallows, Onions, their nature. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Leekes, Parſley, Violets, Dayſie, their nature. 47</item>
               <item>Ielley flower, Marioram, their nature. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Roſemary, Spicknard, Lavender, their nature. 48</item>
               <item>Daffodill, Roſe Campion, Saffron, their nature. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ginger, Wormeſeede, Gallingall, their nature. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Calamus Aromaticus, Acorus, their nature. 49</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of humane Creatures, &amp;c.</head>
               <item>WHat man is, and the manner of his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. 49</item>
               <item>What a feeling ſoule is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Senſes outward, as Touching, Hearing. 50</item>
               <item>Taſting, Smelling. 51</item>
               <item>Sences inward, as Conceiving, Preſerving. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17567:8"/>
               <item>Sleepe, how cauſed. 52</item>
               <item>Waking, how cauſed. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dreames what they are, and their variety. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The nightmare, how occaſioned. 53</item>
               <item>A Trance, what it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Appetite, what it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Motion what it is. 54</item>
               <item>Of the bodies of living creatures. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the matter of the body is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conception, what it is. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Naturall. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Extraordinary 55</item>
               <item>Of the parts of the body: <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Humours, as Blood, Phlegme, Glew. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spirits. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vitall, Animall, what they are. 57</item>
               <item>Griſtles, Sweate, what they are. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Braine, what it is. 58</item>
               <item>Excrements of the braine, eares, and noſe. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The breathing parts. 59</item>
               <item>Heart, Spittle, midriffe, ſtomack<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what they are. 60</item>
               <item>Throat, Vomiting, Liver, what they are. 61</item>
               <item>Vrine. 62</item>
               <item>How to diſcerne a ſound body by it. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Complexions. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dyet. 63</item>
               <item>Guts, their ſeverall kinds. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How placed in the body. <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The diſtinction of living creatures, and their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall kinds. 64</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17567:8"/>
            <head>Naturall Philoſophy.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What Philoſophie is.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Hiloſophie is a knowledge of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall<note place="margin" type="runSum">What Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy is.</note> things. Things (her ſubject) either are He who alone is; from, by, and for whom all things are: or elſe ſuch they be as are numbred by time, and meaſured by place, and ſubject unto motion. God is a Spirit, infinitely good and great.<note place="margin" type="runSum">What God is.</note> God is but one divine Eſſence, conſiſting of three diſtinct Perſons, the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi> The actions of God are either, the Creating or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning<note place="margin" type="runSum">The actions of God two<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fold,</note> of the world. The World conſiſteth either of things inviſible, as of Spirits: or Viſible, as the heavens, the elements, and the bodyes compoſed of elements. The heaven of the bleſſed, <hi>vide Gen.</hi> 1, 1. is counted the third heaven, the Orbes are the ſecond, the Ayre is counted the firſt. The third Heaven viſible is of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances<note place="margin" type="runSum">What Angels are.</note> moſt perfect. The inviſible Spirits, viz. Angels were created heere. Angell ſignifieth a meſſenger, by<note place="margin" type="runSum">How they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</note> nature hee is a ſpirit. Angells appeare ſometime in dreames and viſions, ſometime in bodies apparant
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17567:9"/> and ſometimes in true and reall bodies: their number is great; their office is to celebrate Gods glory, to watch<note place="margin" type="runSum">What their office is.</note> over the world, to preſerve us, to declare and do Gods will, to put good motions into our mindes, to reſiſt ill ſpirits. The Devils were Angels caſt from heaven for ſin, into the lower parts of the World, and heere they continue ſeeking to deface the Image of God in man and all creatures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of motions, qualities, colours, taſting, ſmelling &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THings viſible contained in the world, are Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or Accidents. Accidents are either ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to all things, as motion, time, and place, for theſe belong to all: or proper to ſome things, as Qualities.</p>
               <p>There be two kinde of Movers. 1 God. 2 Things<note place="margin" type="runSum">Two kinde of movers in the world. How created things move.</note> created by him.</p>
               <p>Things created move from God, and are of finite power in moving in a prefixed matter, and in time. They be of two kindes, without, or within the thing moved; the one called violent, the other naturall: Motion is an unperfect act, moving to that it was not,<note place="margin" type="runSum">What motion is. Five things in motion.</note> from that it was: Five things are in naturall motion, the mover, the thing moved, the terme from which, the terme to which it is moved, and time.</p>
               <p>There bee ſixe kindes of motion, generation, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Six kinds of motion.</note> increaſe, decreaſe, alteration of quality, and change of place.</p>
               <p>Qualities are either manifeſt, or ſecret: Manifeſt<note place="margin" type="runSum">What quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are.</note> are either principall, or ſuch as proceede from them:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17567:9"/> the chiefe of the principall, are heate and colde.</p>
               <p>Heate gathereth together things of one kinde, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">What the quality of heate is.</note> ſeparateth things of contrary nature; as Gold from Silver or droſſe. Colde joyneth together things, as the froſt in winter.</p>
               <p>The weaker qualities are moyſture and drineſſe. Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is hardly contained in his owne bounds. Drineſſe keepeth his owne bounds.</p>
               <p>Qualities common from the firſt are either ſeconds or wrought from them.</p>
               <p>Second qualities from one or more, are deriued.</p>
               <p>From Heate commeth Rarity, and Leuity. For<note place="margin" type="runSum">Lightneſſe &amp; thinneſſe commeth of heate.</note> Heate openeth and enlargeth the poores.</p>
               <p>Raritas or Thinnes is that which hath hollow parts or ſpongie as a ſponge, clouds &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Lightnes proceedeth from heate, drawing eaſily<note place="margin" type="runSum">Heavineſſe &amp; thickneſſe of colde.</note> upward. Thicknes and heavines, are of colde. For cold gathereth together, and ſtoppeth bodyes, by which, bodyes become heavie.</p>
               <p>Thicknes hath his parts ſhut up together as ſtones.</p>
               <p>Heavines, moveth downewards: thus is Mercurie, heavier than gold, and gold than Lead.</p>
               <p>Tactile or qualities that may bee touched: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming<note place="margin" type="runSum">What procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from moyſture.</note> from moiſture, are ſoftnes: and tenuitie from the Ayre: ſmoothnes and ſlipperines from the water.</p>
               <p>From dryneſſe proceede hardnes and roughnes, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines<note place="margin" type="runSum">What from drineſſe.</note> in breaking and drought.</p>
               <p>From the firſt qualities diverſly diſpoſed, ariſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers called ſenſible qualities.</p>
               <p>Their Originall is obſcure or more manifeſted.</p>
               <p>Qualities of obſcure originall, are ſuch as doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes plainely &amp; clearely declare the ground whence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17567:10"/> they ariſe. Of this nature are colours: which is the<note place="margin" type="runSum">The uſe of Colours.</note> ſplendor of the body, illuſtrated by light, with which all bodies are dyed according to their moyſtnes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted more or leſſe apt to receive greater, or ſmaller light. Colour, is either ſimple or mixed.</p>
               <p>A Simple colour conſiſts of none other, as black<note place="margin" type="runSum">What a ſimple colour it.</note> and white.</p>
               <p>White conſiſteth of much light in a thin body, of<note place="margin" type="runSum">White what it is.</note> an ayery moiſture well concocted.</p>
               <p>Blacke, is in a thicke body contayning but ſmall<note place="margin" type="runSum">Blacke what it is.</note> light, of moyſture either aduſt or raw watriſh mixed with the earth: as appeareth in the inner parts of the earth.</p>
               <p>Mixt colours are from thoſe two, mingled either in<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of mixt cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors and whence they proceede. And how compounded.</note> a meane or unequall-portion, of equall mixture is red. Other are made of this meane, and one of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames. Yeallow is of much white and a little red, viz. two parts of white and one of red. Saffron cullour or Orange-tawny, is of greater redneſſe, and of leſſer whiteneſſe.</p>
               <p>Purple is of much red, and leſſe blacke. Greene is of much black and leſſe red. This being a cleare moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is moſt pleaſant to the eye.</p>
               <p>Qualities, of a more manifeſt originall are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived<note place="margin" type="runSum">Taſting whence it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds: diverſe kinds of it.</note> in ſmels and taſtes. Taſte is made from the ſtraining of dryneſſe through moiſture, is either hot or cold, in a high or meaneſt degree. Very hot taſtes are biting, bitter, or ſalt.</p>
               <p>Taſtes meanely hot or ſweet: Cold taſts are either thicker or thinner, thicke as ſoure and ſharpe: or thin as tartnes: where alſo we place freſhneſſe.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Smelling whence it proceeds</note>
               </p>
               <p>Smell, is a qualitie comming from a dry earthly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17567:10"/> heate, made thin by mixture of vapors. If it be well<note place="margin" type="runSum">When good when bad.</note> mingled, it is good: if not, it is ſtincking.</p>
               <p>Theſe qualities come from the firſt, there are others<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qualities ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by meanes what they be.</note> that come by Meanes from the firſt, ſuch are, genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fleſh by drineſſe, and binding in, healing and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin" type="runSum">Hid qualities how knowne.</note> together, but more moderate. Hid qualities are onely knowen by long experience, comming from the forme and eſſence of a thing, which in moſt things maketh it hard to diſcerne. Hid qualities are either<note place="margin" type="runSum">They are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther native or pasſionate. Native gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the heavens. How and when of moſt efficacie.</note> inbred or paſſionate. Native or inbred, come from formes taking their originall from heaven, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are governed, moſt according to the poſition of the heavens and ſtars, being of moſt efficacy in their ſubject matter rightly prepared, and at certaine times.</p>
               <p>As the Load-ſtone in drawing Iron. The Pionie for falling ſickneſſe, Polypody in the diſeaſes of the liver, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Paſſionate qualities, are effected by an agreeing or<note place="margin" type="runSum">Paſſionate how effected</note> diſagreeing concord.</p>
               <p>Concord is the naturall agreement of things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<note place="margin" type="runSum">What Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord is.</note> a feirce Bull tied to a fig-tree is made gentle.</p>
               <p>An Olife taken up and replanted by a virgin, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth aboundance of fruite.</p>
               <p>Ocymum a Pulſe, being at the ſowing banned groweth the better: The bleeding of a dead body at the preſence of the killer. Diſcord in naturall things,<note place="margin" type="runSum">What diſcord</note> whereby the horſe-fly is killed with the ſmell of roſes: ſo goats are poyſonous unto plants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17567:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Celeſtiall bodies, as the Heavens, the Firmament, the Starres, with their places, order and government.</head>
               <p>NAturall things are ſimple or compact: Simple are ſtable or unconſtant; ſtable are the heaven and ſtarres. Heaven is as it were a vaulted body made<note place="margin" type="runSum">What heaven is.</note> of water, thinne like a skinne, and moveable.</p>
               <p>The Firmament is the orbe of the moveable hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:<note place="margin" type="runSum">What the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament is.</note> containing the world, which conſiſteth of Ethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall and elementall parts.</p>
               <p>The Ethereall part compaſſeth the Elementall: and<note place="margin" type="runSum">What the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereall part of it is.</note> is not variable: it containeth 10. ſpheres, and is in continuall motion being moved from the Eaſt, to the Weſt in 24. houres, and maketh the naturall day. A ſtar<note place="margin" type="runSum">What a Starre is. The diverſe kinds of them.</note> is a firme eſſence, in heaven, giving light. One ſtar is brighter than another, and they are of divers motion, either ſimple, as from weſt to the eaſt; or divers, as their variable motion, north and ſouth: and they have<note place="margin" type="runSum">Their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, &amp; how it is.</note> their operation over inferiour bodies, which they worke by themſelves, or by aſpect with others; which is either conjunct, or oppoſite: conjunct, is either in the ſame or ſeverall places: ☌. ☍. <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>. <g ref="char:trine">△</g>. caracters bee of conjunction ☌. Sextile ⚹, Trine <g ref="char:trine">△</g>: quadrat <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>: op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ☍, aſpects. Their Poeticke riſing or falling is<note place="margin" type="runSum">Their riſing and falling, &amp; how it is.</note> either true or apparant, the true is Acronicke, which is of ſuch ſtarres as riſe and ſet about the ſunne ſetting: Coſmicke aſcend with the ☉ and ſet with the ſun riſing. Thoſe ſtarres which riſe Coſmically fal Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronically. Apparent riſing is called Helical which is of ſtars getting out of the ſun beames, &amp; ſo if the ſtar get into the ☉ beames at ſetting: or when any ſtar ſetteth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17567:11"/> with the ſun. Starrs are either fixed or wandring,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Stars fixed or wandring.</note> ſixed are the ſtarres of the firmament, whoſe motion is not ſenſible; For in 72. yeares they move ſcarce a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree:<note place="margin" type="runSum">How knowne from Planets.</note> keeping ſtill one like diſtance. Stars are knowne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> planets, by their twinkling. The ſtars are far bigger in compaſſe than the earth, and they are of ſixfoold order, firſt bigger than the earth, 107. fold, ſecond 87. third 72. forth 54. fift 31. ſixt 18. times. Theſe ſtars are more or leſſe gliſtering: the moſt gliſtering are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed into 48. Images and are devided into three parts the zodiack &amp; both ſides thereof. The zodiack contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth<note place="margin" type="runSum">How and where contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the heavens.</note> 12 ſignes, ♈. ♉. ♊. ♋. ♌. ♍. ♎. ♐. ♑. ♒. ♊. of the Eaſt are ♈. ♌. ♐. fiery ſignes. North ♋ ♏. ♓. watery. ♊. ♎. ♒. Ayery of the Weſt: ♉. ♍. ♑. earthy Southern ſignes.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Stars Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line &amp; Femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine.</note> Fiery and Ayery are Maſculine: Wateriſh ſignes and earthly feminine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries</hi> the Ram is the firſt ſigne of the Zodiacke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting<note place="margin" type="runSum">Aries.</note> of 13. ſtarres, repreſenting the image of a Ram, it hath 2. ſtarres in his horne of the 3. bignes and 3. in his taile, and one in the tippe of his right ſoote of the 4. bignes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> the Bull conſiſteth of 32. ſtarres, 5. of theſe<note place="margin" type="runSum">Taurus.</note> in his forehead are called <hi>Hyades,</hi> cauſing raine, the greateſt is called the Bulls eye, being ſomewhat pale. 7. ſtarres in his ſhoulder are little and called <hi>Vergiliae,</hi> and <hi>Pleiades,</hi> becauſe they ſhew the time of navigation by their riſing in the Spring and ſetting in the Autum.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gemini</hi> the twins of 18. ſtarres; in each head, is a<note place="margin" type="runSum">Gemini.</note> bright ſtar, called <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cancer</hi> the Crab conſiſteth of 9. ſtarres ſomewhat<note place="margin" type="runSum">Cancer.</note> obſcure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the Lyon is a bright ſigne of 27. ſtarres, one in his<note place="margin" type="runSum">Leo.</note>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17567:12"/> heart and one in his tayle, are of the firſt bignes, neare his tayle are 7. ſtarres called <hi>Berenices</hi> haire.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Virgo.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vîrgo</hi> the maide with wings of 26. ſtarres, one in her left hand is called <hi>Spica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libra</hi> the ballance is expreſſed with 8. ſtarres.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Libra.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scorpion</hi> hath 21. ſtarres, of which but 14. are notable.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Scorpion.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sagitarius</hi> the Archer conſiſteth of 31. ſtarres.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Sagitarius.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Capricornus</hi> the Goat, hath 18. ſtarres, of which 12.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Capricornus</note> are moſt conſpicuous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquarius</hi> the water-bearer, of 24. ſtarres, like a man<note place="margin" type="runSum">Aquarius.</note> pouring water fourth of his pitcher, the ſtarre in the extreame of the water is of the firſt bignes. totall. 364.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Piſces.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſces,</hi> the fiſhes conſiſt of 34. ſtarres.</p>
               <p>The other ſtarres that are not in the Zodiack are<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of Stars not in the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke. What the nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations.</note> either northerne or ſoutherne ſtarres.</p>
               <p>The Northerne Conſtellations are <hi>Cynoſura,</hi> the little Beare hath 7 Starres. Helice the greater Beare hath 27 ſtarres, of which 12 are more viſible. Draco the Snake 31. Bootes the Heardman 22. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt whoſe legs is Arctur. Ariadnes Crowne 8. Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules 28. Cepheus 11. The Vultur or Lira 10. The Swan 17. Caſſiopeia 13. Perſeus 19. The Carter 13. he beareth upon his left ſhoulder the Goat, Aeſculapius 24. The Serpent 18. ſtarres. The Arrow 5. The Eagle 6. The Dolphin 10. Pegaſus 20. The foale 4. Andromeda 23. ſtarres. The Triangle hath 4 ſtarres. The totall 360.</p>
               <p>The Southern conſtellations are 25. The Whale<note place="margin" type="runSum">What the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations are.</note> hath 22 Starres.</p>
               <p>Orion hath 38. Eridanus 34. The Hare 12. The great Dog 18. The Whelpe 2. The ſhip 45. Hydra 5.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17567:12"/> The Crow 7. The Centaure 37. The Wolfe 19. The Aulter 17. The Crowne 13. The fiſh 12. Starres. The totall 316.</p>
               <p>Plannets are Starres in the neaver part of Heaven,<note place="margin" type="runSum">What Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets are. Why called wandring.</note> and are of diverſe motions, and are therefore called wandring, which motions happen not according to the courſe of other Starres, becauſe in the ſpheeres at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the ſeverall plannets, they moving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves circularly are ſtayed either in their higheſt or loweſt Abſis, or elſe are made to goe backward. Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets<note place="margin" type="runSum">When and how they are, ſtayed.</note> are ſtayed when at their ſet bounds they ſtay their courſe and turne to ſome other part, and ſo ſeeme to ſtand ſtill.</p>
               <p>Abſis or Aux, the higheſt place of the Plannets, to which being moved, they can aſcend no higher, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Apogaeon, viz. fartheſt from the earth.</p>
               <p>Abſis or Aux, the loweſt contrary to the other, and neereſt unto us, is called Perigaeon.</p>
               <p>Plannets are ſaid to goe backe, when removing<note place="margin" type="runSum">When and how they goe backe.</note> themſelves, they goe not forward their courſe, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne backe the way they came, in ſome part.</p>
               <p>The vertues and force of Plannets, are as diverſe as<note place="margin" type="runSum">The vertues and force of Plannets.</note> their motions be: ſtronger by the proper habitation of the houſe, or by conjunction: otherwiſe they be weake.</p>
               <p>The proper houſe of each Plannet is that ſigne of<note place="margin" type="runSum">The proper houſe of each Plannets.</note> the Zodiacke, in which firſt at the creation they were placed after the opinion of Aſtronomers.</p>
               <p>Thus farre in generall. Now ſome ſhine with one<note place="margin" type="runSum">Plannets ſome of one light, ſome more.</note> particular light, other with more. They that have the ſame ſhinning, are moved with equall or unequall courſe. Plannets of uneven courſe have a proper mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to themſelves. ♄. ♃. ♂.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17567:13"/>
               <p>Their conjunction is common or ſpeciall. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin" type="runSum">Conjunction of Planets, common or ſpecial.</note> are of theſe three together, and it is called the greateſt conjunction: this through his ſlow motion foreſheweth wonders, as Aſtrologers ſay, though their<note place="margin" type="runSum">They preſage things to come</note> grounds are uncertaine, yet wee will ſet downe what they ſay, not all as truths, yet ſome may bee probable. (Eſpecially the ſunne regarding) deſtruction to king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes<note place="margin" type="runSum">And how.</note> &amp;c. If ſuch conjunction, bee in a fiery ſigne it preſageth great drought. In a watry ſigne it argueth raine, in Aery mighty tempeſtes. In earthy extreame cold. In Maſculine death of men, In feminine death of women. Speciall conjunction is either meane or extreame. Meane of Saturne and Mars betokens warres, contention, ſtrife of Kings and Princes, and to theſe proſperous ſucceſſours, if the dominant be good in conjunction.</p>
               <p>The extreame conjunction of Plannets, is great or leſſe, greater of ♄, ♃. betokening new ſects, and other like. If ♃. be all ſtronger, ſhall be for the beſt, if ♄. be ſtronger, then followeth loſſe, tribulation and great diſcord, ſay the Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>♄. Saturne is a ſtar of a leaden colour, finiſhing his<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of Saturne his properties, how he ruleth in the bodies, and over whom.</note> courſe in thirty yeares, hee is a Plannet maſculine, of cold and dry nature, therefore melancholicke, bad &amp; not fortunate, whoſe proper houſe is in ♑. ♎. gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning malancholike perſons, and diſeaſes of that humor, and thoſe of a tough and congealed phlegme as Lepry and Morphew. But if hee governe in his proper houſe in due aſpect and degree, moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble experiments may bee made againſt theſe infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, His rule appeareth in conception of men, as in the firſt moneth, and in the eight moneth much more.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17567:13"/> Wherefore the child borne in this moneth, through the bad aſpect, and coldnes of Saturne, can ſcarce live long: hee ruleth alſo the lives of men, eſpecially in their end, when old men bee cold and full of fleame, as ſay Aſtrologers.<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of Iupiter. His proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note>
               </p>
               <p>♃ Iupiter is a bright Plannet, which runneth his courſe in 12. yeares, his light is ſo great, that it cauſeth a ſhadow, being neere the earth, of which he is called Phaeton: He is hot and moyſt of nature, good, maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,<note place="margin" type="runSum">How he ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and over whom.</note> and his houſe is in ♐ and ♓ he ruleth over the ſanguine, yong men and merry ſports, and over diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes ſpringing of bloud not aduſt: and rightly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. In his houſe, remedies are beſt applied for cure of ſuch infirmities. Vnder his power is the child in the ſecond, but more in the ninth moneth, and the childe that is borne is long of life.<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of Mars.</note>
               </p>
               <p>♂ Mars, is the 3 wandring ſtar, in colour red or fiery ſhining, his courſe is 2. yeares, is a maſculine exceeding hot, ſchorching and dry nature, after a ſort malignant<note place="margin" type="runSum">His proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. How he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns mans body and in whom.</note> and infortunate: His houſe is ♈ and ♍ hee ſheweth his force moſt upon Cholerike perſons, and upon motions of youth, ſtirring to ſedition and warre: if hee be well diſpoſed in his houſe in fit aſpect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, there may bee remedies uſed for the Frenſie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and other hot ſickneſſes. He governeth the 3. moneth of conception, and from 40. to 50. of mans age.</p>
               <p>Now of ſtarrs, that finiſh their courſe in like ſpace<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of the ſunne. The office and uſe of it. How and whom it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes.</note> of time ☉ ♀. ☿. in a yeare ſpace ☉. The Sunne is the brighteſt of all wandring ſtarres, appointing ſeaſons, nouriſhing life, being the fountaine of light, of heate and all vitall powers, hee is hot and meanely dry, his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17567:14"/> houſe is ♌. he ruleth hot and dry affections, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his rule is fit remedy for ſuch.</p>
               <p>In mans conception hee ruleth the 4. moneth, and governeth from 22. till 41. yeares of age. ☉ by being neareſt or fartheſt from the earth, maketh Solſticium, which is our Summer and Winter: ſummer is ☉, being<note place="margin" type="runSum">He maketh winter and ſummer.</note> in ♋. at the higheſt; winter ſolſtice is ☉, being ♑ fartheſt from us. The motion of ☉, cauſeth like length of day<note place="margin" type="runSum">Length and ſhortneſſe of dayes.</note> and night. ☉, in ♈ and ♎ the Sun in theſe pointes of heaven is equally moved in the 6. ſignes of our hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere, and alſo in the ſix oppoſit, although the points and times of both Equinoctialls vary and change.</p>
               <p>♀ Venus is a very white ſtar, ſhe goeth neare ☉, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of Venus.</note> before him, ſometimes after him; in the morning going before him, ſhe is called Lucifer, in the evening, following, ſhe is called Veſperugo and Heſperus. ♀ is could and Ayery, and moyſt, her houſe is in ☍ and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Her proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: how and in whom ſhe ruleth.</note> ♎. She loveth youth, women, and wives, ruleth cold and moyſt diſeaſes, happening moſt about the geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls. Therefore ♀ in her houſe in due aſpect is beſt remedy of ſuch, ſhe uſeth her power in the 5. moneth, and diſpoſeth life, from 14, to 20. yeares and two, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>☿ Mercury is the leaſt wandring ſtar, ſomwhat white,<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of Mercury. His nature: how and in whom he ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</note> his nature is changeable, and full of turnings, hee is hote with the hote, cold with the cold, of the nature of him with whom he is joyned, his houſe is ♊ and ♍, &amp; is of force in merchandize, of which hee hath his name, and mathematickes are under his rule, he begins and followes ſtudies, &amp; reports rumors &amp; newes. He gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the 6 moneth, and from 4. to 14. yeares; if hee joyne with the higher Plannets, he denounceth wet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17567:14"/> and flouds, which alſo hee doth meeting Venus in a wet houſe, in his proper houſe, windes &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> The Moone is the loweſt wandring ſtarre, fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of the Moone.</note> her courſe in 27. dayes 7. houres; although this ſtarre have light of he owne, yet doth ſhe borrow her ſhining from the Sunne. But becauſe her eſſence or body, is not alike, but thicker in one place, than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, therfore ſhe is not in all places enlightened alike from the Sunne. That part which is turned from the Sunne, is all of it ſhadowed and darkiſh, but that which looketh upon the ☉. is full of light, and onely ſo much light as ſtandeth towards us, ſeemeth to gaine or loſe light, as it is farther off, or nearer the ſun, where as indeed ever the one halfe is enlightened from the ſunne.</p>
               <p>The face ſeemeth to bee enlightened, as joyned with ☉, or departing from him.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> joyned with the ☉ in the 4. firſt dayes is cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with greater light of the ☉ beames, and is called the new Moone, but departing from ☉ ſhe appeareth ſtill more enlightened, and it is either in part or whole.</p>
               <p>In part before and after the 8 day, called the encreaſe<note place="margin" type="runSum">How the Moone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth and decreaſeth.</note> and the waine of the Moone. In part leſſe or more, the leſſe is when ſhe is horned, or halfe moone about the 4. day, being diſtant from ☉ 2. ſignes: and after 8. in the 26. day, the halfe <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is ſeene about the 7. day and after 22. day when ſhe is diſtant 3. ſignes or degrees from ☉. The greater apparition of the Moone in part is, ſhe being neare her roundnes, which is about the 11 day and after the 19. day diſtant from ☉ 4 ſignes.</p>
               <p>The full apparition of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is when in a right line ſhe is<note place="margin" type="runSum">When and how the Moone is in the full.</note> oppoſed to ☉ at 14 dayes or full Moone. Although ſhe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17567:15"/> finiſh her couſe in the foreſaid time in the circle of the Zodiacke, yet is allowed to every Moone 29: and a halfe day, becauſe ſhe is to paſſe forward 2 dayes and 4 howres, before ſhee can overtake the ☉ which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth 29 dayes, 12 houres. And in 9 yeares ſhe endeth<note place="margin" type="runSum">In what time ſhe endeth her revolution.</note> all her diverſity of conjunctions and aſpectes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new begineth her former revolution, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>A Commet is a wandering ſtar, of divers motions,<note place="margin" type="runSum">What a Commet is.</note> ſhining in the region of the Plannets, this appeareth ſeldome, ſometime above, and ſometimes below the Plannets. It foretelleth greevous accidents.</p>
               <p>Others ſay that a Commet is a fat ſubſtance drawne by the heate of the Sun from the earth, and the heate of the higheſt region of the Ayre; is ſet on fire appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring like a ſtarre, and is ſometime moved in the ayre.</p>
               <p>It foreſhewth war, Peſtilence, drought, and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the earth.</p>
               <p>The light of ſome Plannets ſometime fayle, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin" type="runSum">The light of ſome Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets eſpecially the ſunne and moone faileth ſometime, and the reaſon of them.</note> of ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> The defects happen in the Zodiacke, if theſe 2. ſtarres bee in the knotts of their circles, or neare to them; which knotts are cuttings, made by the courſe of the ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and is called the dragon. The higher is called Dragons head, the lower the Dragons tayle. The Aſcendant or higher is where, <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> departing from the middle Zodiacke, doth come neareſt unto us.</p>
               <p>The deſcendant, when the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is removing from us.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of the Eclipſe of the Sunne and Moone and the reaſon of them.</note> The Eclipſe of thoſe ſtarrs is in whole or part. In whole all being obſcured, as in the midſt of them.</p>
               <p>In part it happeneth neare one of the knotts.</p>
               <p>The Eclipſe of ☉, is by comming of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> betweene our eyes and the ☉, in the conjunction of both Plannets.</p>
               <p>A great Eclipſe of ☉, is when the centure of theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17567:15"/> ſtarres, proceed in a direct line to our eye.</p>
               <p>The Eclipſe of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is the depriving her of the light of ☉, in the oppoſition, the earth ſhadowing her, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in a ſtraight line betweene them; her Eclipſe is ſooner ſeene in the Eaſt than in the Weſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the foure Elements.</head>
               <p>ELements are ſimple eſſences, leſſe durable than the<note place="margin" type="runSum">What Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are.</note> heavens, and are the wombs of mixed things &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Of the Elements 2. are cleare, ayre and water. Ayre,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Some cleare as Ayre and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of the Ayre.</note> which is cold and moyſt, and of theſe there are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed 3. regions, the firſt is hot and dry, this is termed the fiery which cauſeth it to be called an Element Ayre the flame being but inflamed ayre: the midle region colder and darker; the third region, in which we live, is hot and cold, by the more or leſſe reflection of the Sunne beames.</p>
               <p>Ayre, is ſo needefull to creatures, that none live<note place="margin" type="runSum">The neceſsity of the Ayre.</note> without it, the thinner the better, and more healthfull.</p>
               <p>Water, is an element leſſe thin and cleare, moyſt and<note place="margin" type="runSum">What water is. The natures and uſes of it.</note> moſt cold. Water warmed in channells in the earth cauſeth hot ſprings, this is heated by running by ſome hot mineralls, and helpeth moyſt and cold bodies.</p>
               <p>Water, is greater or leſſe. The greateſt is the Sea,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Why the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ſea is ſalt. The reaſon of the ebbing and flowing of the ſea.</note> which is ſalt, becauſe that the ſtarres drawe ſorth the thin ſubſtance leaving the earth behinde. The Ocean ebbeth and floweth after the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> motion; and from the new moone to the full, humours increaſe and after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and the tides are knowne by the Moone. Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Seas take their name of ſome country, or of ſome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17567:16"/> accident, as the red Sea, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Waters are in flouds or fountaines, fountaines are<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of Flouds &amp; Fountaines.</note> beſt which come out of Mountaines, or Rocks, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Water is of divers colours and taſtes. Milky,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Diverſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours &amp; taſtes of waters. What the earth is.</note> Greene, Red, Salt, ſharpe, bitter, and like wine.</p>
               <p>The Earth is a thicke element, cold and dry, and is unmoveable, about which all things move, it is round and all things tend as neare the center as they can.</p>
               <p>It is in compaſſe with the water 21600. miles, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">The compaſſe of it.</note> is but as a point to the whole world.</p>
               <p>Concreat and mixt bodyes or natures, are eſſences<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of concreat &amp; mixt bodies</note> mixt of parts ſeverally diſpoſed. For from ſundry things of divers formes, one forme may bee formed: and things of one mixture according to the divers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of their elements are diverſly affected.</p>
               <p>As ſome are Ayery, ſome Fiery, and ſome Earthly. But the proportion maketh temperature, which is a proportion of qualities, cleaving together in mixture: it is equall or uneven, and is either ſimple or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound: ſimple is in act or power: compound, as heate with drineſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Mixed natures are either liveleſſe or living. Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſ<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of mixed liveleſſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors; &amp; what they be, with their ſeverall kinds, and the reaſon of them.</note> as Meteors which are a hot ſmoake lifted up by the attractive force of ſtarres, ſome 15. German miles into the ayre and no higher: this ſmoke is a vapour or exhalation. A vapour is a moyſt ſmoke drawne from water, and is eaſily reſolved into water. Exhalation is a dry ſmoke drawne from the earth, eaſie to fire: from exhalation ariſe fiery impreſſions which burne like fire, as pillers, dartes, candles, goates, ſhooting ſtarres, fiery Dragons, darke ſtreames, fooles fire, and ſuch like firery Meteors.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17567:16"/>
               <p>Mixed fiery meteors whoſe exhalation is ſomewhat<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of Mixed fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meteors, as thunder, what it is, and the reaſon of it.</note> unpure thicker and long, her mixture is thunder which is a fiery exhalation, breaking forth of the cloudes, with a ſound. Lightening ſmall and great is a flaming light, of a burning exhalation, ſhining be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thunder. Though we heare not the thunder, it is at the preſent breaking out of the flaſh, the eye being quicker than the care. The great lightening is thicker and burneth more, if it be hardened with the heate of the Sunne, and it ſelfe, it maketh a ſtone which is caſt out at the cracke, this doth much harme.</p>
               <p>Lightening is thicke or thin, this boreth through<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of lightning; what it is, and the reaſon of it.</note> without leaving any ſigne of it. The thicker ſcorcheth and burneth, it hath much earthy matter, ſetting on fier ſteeples and ſuch like, and in great flaſhes is but ſome ſmall deale of this earthy matter, elſe all things would be fired.</p>
               <p>Watery meteors, are vapors more fully compact to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of watery meteors, as clouds, what they be, with the reaſon of them.</note> and appeare in the loweſt part, or midſt of the Ayre, as cloudes and ſuch like. A cloude is a vapour joyned together by the extreame cold of the middle region. Cloudes hang in the Ayre by the Sunnes heat, which draweth them up, and by the moving of the windes are toſſed up and downe.</p>
               <p>In theſe Cloudes by ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, are framed divers<note place="margin" type="runSum">Diverſe ſhapes in the cloudes, with the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of them: as a falſe Sunne, how occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</note> ſhapes, having no proper matter, but onely appeare in the cloudes, either about ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, or oppoſite to them as:</p>
               <p>A halfe Sunne which is imprinted in the Cloud by the reflection of his beames, in a cloud being wateriſh, ſo that ſometime the ſhape of 2. or 3. Sunnes are ſeene, ſo of the Moone. Bright circles of the cloudes, being
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17567:17"/> black, are from the reflecting beames, ſeeming to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the ☉ or <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> yet they are far lower. Theſe circles appeare more often about the moone: ſhee being not able with her beames to conſume theſe vapours.</p>
               <p>The ſhape in the cloudes oppoſed to the Sunne, is<note place="margin" type="runSum">A raine-bow how occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</note> the raine-bow of divers colours, in a hollow, thin and in an unequall cloud, faſhioned by reflection of the Suns beames, and the raine-bow is greater the nearer it commeth to the Horizon. If many raine-bowes be ſeene, the latter is made by the ſhining of the other, and are more obſcure than the former.</p>
               <p>The colours of the Raine-bow, be light, red, green;<note place="margin" type="runSum">A deſcription of the raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow and the ſignes oſ it.</note> ſky colour and yeallow: the raine-bow, is a foreteller of raine, it ſheweth that many vapours are diſſolued, which will ſhortly be raine. The hayle is like this, but it is alwayes under the Sunne.</p>
               <p>Meteors of diſſolved cloudes, are either hardened,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Meteors of diſſolued cloudes.</note> or moyſt, as raine, which is as it were a cloude melted and turned unto water; if the cloude bee neare the earth the drops are great, if hie, the drops are ſmaller. The rayning of frogges, fiſh, milke, fleſh, and ſuch like, come of ſuch matter being carried up, which doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon of it.</note> fall with the raine, as wormes &amp;c. are begotten of dead carkaſes in ſummer time.</p>
               <p>Meteors made harde, after the cloud hath beene melted, are ſnow and Haile.</p>
               <p>Snow is a cloude, prepared for raine before it fall,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Snow what it is and how occaſioned.</note> being congealed by cold, is by the motion of the windes diſperſed into fleakes, and falleth onely in winter.</p>
               <p>Hayle is rayne, made hard in the fall, the higher the<note place="margin" type="runSum">Hayle what it is and how occaſioned.</note> fall, the rounder and leſſer, becauſe in the fall it mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17567:17"/> It hayleth moſt in Autumne and in the Spring, for then the ſharpe ayre, hath moſt power over the drops, and in winter, the extreame cold maketh it ſnow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet in the cloudes.</p>
               <p>In the loweſt region of the Ayre, are dew and froſt.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Dew what it is, and how occaſioned.</note> Dew is a vapour thickned with ſome earthly matter, which in falling is preſently turned into water.</p>
               <p>Dew falleth onely in ſummer, for then the vapour is diſſolved with the Sunne.</p>
               <p>A fat kind of dew like melting hony, eſpecially at the ſhining of Syrius, being gathered from leaves of trees, is Manna, called alſo wilde honey, or meldewes.</p>
               <p>This Manna hardened by the heate of ☉ into<note place="margin" type="runSum">Manna what it is.</note> lumpes, is called Tereniabin.</p>
               <p>Froſt is a dewiſh vapour, made very hard by cold in<note place="margin" type="runSum">Froſt what it is, and how.</note> winter before it be diſſolved.</p>
               <p>Meteors made of both kindes of ſmoake joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of Meteors cauſed by both<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> kinds of ſmoake, and the reaſon of them. Winde what it is, and the diverſe kinds of it.</note> are windes and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Winde is a ſubtile ſmoke, beaten downeward by the cold in the middle of the ayre, and is moved ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the earth: Auncients noted out 12. principall windes, all which in regard of matter are hot and dry, but differ for their ſituation of their qualities.</p>
               <p>The winde being great, carried with force, darkens<note place="margin" type="runSum">Storme. Whirlewinde.</note> the Ayre, and is called a ſtorme. If it doe roll about, it is a Whirle-winde, if it be but ſmall, it is called Ayre.</p>
               <p>An Earthquake is a fume, contained in the earth:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Earthquake.</note> when it findeth no vent, it ſhaketh it, &amp; is made acoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the breadth or depth of the earth. In breadth it cauſeth ſometime ſuch trembling, that it ſhaketh downe whole Citties. That in depth cauſeth a gaping or ſwelling. A Gaping is when the Earth openeth,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17567:18"/> as it were her mouth, and doth ſwallow downe trees, walles &amp;c. A Swelling is when the earth being lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up like a mountaine, either remaineth ſo, or elſe falleth downe againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of mixed living Natures.</head>
               <p>NAtures mixed perfectly are living and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſſences, indued with a Vegetative ſoule; A Vegetative ſoule is a facultie giving life to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes.<note place="margin" type="runSum">What a vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative ſoule is.</note> Therefore ſo long as any part of this ſhall exerciſe her power in any body, ſo long is that alive, and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſafe. But her chiefe operation, and ſo life it ſelfe,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature &amp; office of it.</note> conſiſteth either in preſerving ſeverall bodies or whole kinds. Nouriſhment is the preſerving of ſeverall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,<note place="margin" type="runSum">What nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment is.</note> and is the making of foode received, like to the body nouriſhed. Vnder that name is every thing which is received to ſuſtaine our bodyes, of which ſort is the ayre it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Some other faculties are required to perfection of nouriſhment, as concoction, and his companions: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction<note place="margin" type="runSum">What cócocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, with the neceſsity of it.</note> is a working or framing of nouriſhment, and it is made either of temperate, or increaſed heate of the parts to be nouriſhed.</p>
               <p>By temperate heate is made ripening: which is a<note place="margin" type="runSum">The neceſsity of temperate heate for nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</note> concoction of nouriſhment with moiſture, by how much therefore the moiſture ſhall be better tempered with heate, by ſo much is the ripening ſooner, and more perfect, as in a ſummer too moyſt, the increaſe of the earth is later made ripe. Concoction ariſing from greater ſtore of heate, is either elixation or aſſation.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17567:18"/> Elixation is a concoction more perfectly working the thicke or watriſh moyſture, with a ſtrong moyſt heate: As fleſh is ſod in water, whoſe moyſt heate altereth &amp; conſumeth the fomy moyſtnes of meate: if this Elixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion remaine unperfect, it is called rawneſſe, and the nouriſhment is not refined, for want of moyſt heate: For it was not of power to finiſh concoction.</p>
               <p>Aſſation is concoction, by meanes of dryer heate fully ſtrengthening the moyſture of nouriſhment. If<note place="margin" type="runSum">The benefit of good, and the hurt of bad concoction.</note> this ſtrength of bodyes be ſomewhat weake, it is called thickning; if concoction bee vicious, it is turned unto putrifaction. Moyſt and hote things doe moſt eaſily corrupt, if the bodyes be not open to the Ayre.</p>
               <p>In ſtopped bodyes, heate having no vent is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Whence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation ariſeth.</note> Whence commeth inflammation, which putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction doth follow, cauſing greater heate. This of concoction.</p>
               <p>The Companions of concoction, are Faculties, fitly<note place="margin" type="runSum">The compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.</note> ſerving for the perfection of it.</p>
               <p>Of theſe, one goeth before, the other followeth. The former is Attraction and Retention.</p>
               <p>Attraction is a facultie, ſupplying matter of conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient<note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Attraction, what it is.</note> nouriſhment, as is ſeene in things drawing our of the fleſh Arrow-heads or thornes deepely faſtned. So wheat draweth water out of on earthen pot, it being ſet upon the heape. Retention which retayneth<note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Retention, what it is.</note> nouriſhment, untill it be concocted, &amp; doth nouriſh the body. Nouriſhment, is firſt put to and afterward united. The companion following concoction is expulſion.</p>
               <p>Expulſion, is a driving backe of unprofitable matter:<note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Expulſion, what it is.</note> when concoction is once made, it is within or without
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17567:19"/> the body. Within, when the ſtronger thruſt ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the weaker, untill they come to the weakeſt of all. Encreaſe which is joyned to the nouriſhment, is continued but to a certaine age, &amp; then the nouriſhing growing weake it ceaſeth. Now followeth conſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole ſtocke.</p>
               <p>Generation is a facultie of the body, procreating any<note place="margin" type="runSum">What genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is.</note> thing like it ſelfe. This faculty preſerveth all kindes of things in their eſtate, though continually they doe periſh.</p>
               <p>The object of generation, is the procreating ſeede<note place="margin" type="runSum">What is the object of it.</note> of every thing.</p>
               <p>The changing faculty, altereth the ſeede into parts of the body to be begotten.</p>
               <p>The miniſteriall vertues of this facultie of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doe change or forme.</p>
               <p>The forming faculty faſhioneth the thing into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct forme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Minerals and Mettals.</head>
               <p>THe Vegetative ſoule being explained: now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the kindes of ſuch natures as have perfect, or unperfect growth. Thoſe of unperfect growth are Mettals, which are decocted in the veines of the earth. Mettals are to be melted eaſily or hardly. Thoſe that are eaſie to bee diſſolved, are either firſt, or ſuch as ſpring from them.</p>
               <p>Principall, or firſt, are of themſelves from the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Brimſtone what it is, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it.</note> as Brimſtome, and Quickſilver.</p>
               <p>Brimſtone is the fat of the earth, with fiery heate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17567:19"/> unto his hardneſſe, which is the cauſe that it ſo ſpeedily is enflamed, and burneth even in water, yea ſooner than the fat of the beaſts, which though it bee fatter than brimſtone, yet it is farre colder. So that for his fat drineſſe, it helpeth ſcabbes of all kinds, and the leprie.</p>
               <p>That Brimſtone is counted the beſt, which is greene and cleare.</p>
               <p>Quickſilver is a ſlimy water, mixt with a pure white<note place="margin" type="runSum">Quickſilver, what it is.</note> earth, which mettall for the matter whereof it doth conſiſt, is thinne, cold, and heavie.</p>
               <p>It is in continuall motion, and his thinneſſe cauſeth<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> that it pierceth mettals.</p>
               <p>Mettals derived from the firſt, are more or leſſe<note place="margin" type="runSum">Gold what it is.</note> pure; purer, are Gold and Silver. Gold is a mettall made of moſt ſubtile and pure red brimſtone, and of the like quickſilver. Gold hath the moſt perfect mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as it is moſt thin, ſo it is moſt ſolide, whoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is not corrupted, with either earth, water, or ayre, nor conſumed with fire, but is more purged in it.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And for his thin ſolidneſſe, it is moſt ſoft, and eaſie to be melted. So that is moſt worth, which is moſt red and gliſtering and ſoft, that eaſily it may be wrought.</p>
               <p>Experience teacheth, that the 3 part of one graine of gold can gild a wyre of 134 foote long: upon plates of ſilver, one ounce of gold will ſuffice to gild eight pound waight of ſilver. His nature is to bee marvelled at. It waxeth cold towards day light, ſo that thoſe that weare rings of it, may perceive it, when it waxeth day.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Where it is found.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It is found in the mountaines of Arabia and elſe where; and the beſt, in the mountaine Terrat, neare the Citie Corbachiam.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17567:20"/>
               <p>Siluer is a mettall begotten of pure white Mercury,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Silver, what it is. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt it and gold.</note> and the like cleare white Brimſtone. It differeth from Gold almoſt onely in colour, it being Gold not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly refined; yet in pureneſſe, firme ſolidneſſe, and thinneſſe, it is next to Gold, and one ounce of it may be drawne 3200. foote long, ſo that it can ſcarce be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned from Gold. Yet it is thicker an hundreth fold.</p>
               <p>When it is found, it hath the ſhape of haires, twigs, fiſhes, ſerpents, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Mettals leſſe pure, conſiſt of greater ſtore of Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone or Quickſilver; of greater ſtore of Brimſtone, come Braſſe, and Iron.</p>
               <p>Braſſe is a mettall, begotten of thicke red Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Braſſe what it is.</note> and Mercury ſomewhat impure; that comming from Cyprus, is called Copper: the matter of Braſſe is more burnt than that of other mettals, and indureth long, and is fit in any worke. For it is without all moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, whether it be kept in earth or water. Minerals neare Braſſe are Copperaſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Copperaſſe, is a minerall mixed of humours ſtrained<note place="margin" type="runSum">Copperaſſe, what it is.</note> by droppes into ſmall holes, and it ſhineth like glaſſe.</p>
               <p>It is hot and dry in the 4. degree, vehemently bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> being of great force to ſeaſon and preſerve raw fleſh. It alſo begetteth ſound fleſh in feſtered ſores, and ſtancheth blood. It is of a greene, yellow, and a skye colour, the beſt hath in it white ſpots; his kinde are Romane vitrioll, and red vitrioll, or the fome of Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraſſe.</p>
               <p>Iron is of ſtore of Mercury, and of thicke ſulphur,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Iron, what it is.</note> impure and aduſt. It may be ſoftened by quenching in<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> juyce of beane ſhuls or mallowes. It being red hot
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17567:20"/> and cooling of himſelfe, becommeth plyable.</p>
               <p>But if it be often quenched in cold water, it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thereby, very hard and brittle.</p>
               <p>Mettalls of greater ſtore of Mercury, are Lead and Tynne.</p>
               <p>Lead is an unpure mettall, begot of much unpure<note place="margin" type="runSum">Lead, what it is.</note> thicke and droſſie Mercury, and likewiſe of unpure Brimſtone; his impurity cauſeth blackneſſe, which by refining is made whiter. It increaſeth in waight, if it lie in moyſt ground.</p>
               <p>Yea it is thought to increaſe with raine. It is of a<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> cold and binding nature, and therefore ſcarce whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for mans uſe.</p>
               <p>Tynne is a mettall mixed of Mercury, white with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<note place="margin" type="runSum">Tynne, what it is.</note> and red within, and of Brimſtone not well mixed, as it were Lead whited with ſilver.</p>
               <p>Thus farre of mettalls pliable.</p>
               <p>Mettals leſſe plyable are thoſe which are not eaſily wrought, or melted, and are hard or brittle.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that bee altogether hard, are ſtones. Theſe<note place="margin" type="runSum">Stones, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are, &amp;c the variety of them.</note> are ingendred of a watry moyſture, and fat earth mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hard togeather. Of ſtones, ſome be rare, ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Of the rare and ſtrange, ſome are of more eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation than others.</p>
               <p>The more eſteemed are precious ſtones; which are<note place="margin" type="runSum">Precious ſtones.</note> more beautifull and fine, in regard of their pure and ſubtile matter: Of Gemmes ſome are of one coullour, ſome of ſundry colours. More or leſſe tranſparent be either white, or of other colours.</p>
               <p>White are Cryſtall or Adamant. Cryſtall is a<note place="margin" type="runSum">Cryſtall.</note> gem, bright through, begot of a moſt pure ſtony moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> and is found in mines of Marble, &amp;c. His quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17567:21"/> is binding: therefore his oyle or powder is helpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Laxes, and increaſeth milke in womens breſts.</p>
               <p>The Adamant or Diamant is a gem cleare and moſt<note place="margin" type="runSum">Adamant.</note> hard, it can ſcarce be broken (and thence it is named)<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> unleſſe ſteeped in the warme bloud of a Goat that hath drunke Wine or eaten Parſley.</p>
               <p>Tranſparent Gemmes not white, as the Saphir Sardonix, and Smaragde, have the ſame coullour in all their kindes.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Saphir.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Saphir is a gem cleare through, of a skie coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, growing in the Eaſt, and ſpecially in India:<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> Being drunke, it helpeth againſt the ſtinging of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, poyſon, &amp;c. as ſome affirme.</p>
               <p>The Smaragde is of a greene coullour, making<note place="margin" type="runSum">Smaragde.</note> greene the ayre neare about it; the ſtone of Brytaine<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> is the beſt. It preſerveth the wearer from the falling ſickeneſſe: eyght graines of his ſhaving drunke, expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth poyſon, &amp;c. as ſome affirme.</p>
               <p>The Sardonyx is a cleare gem, repreſenting in coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours<note place="margin" type="runSum">Sardonyx.</note> the nayle of a mans hand: it preſerveth chaſtnes,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> and healeth vlcers about the nayles.</p>
               <p>The Selenites is a tranſparent gem like glaſſe, it<note place="margin" type="runSum">Selenites.</note> ſeemeth to increaſe and decreaſe with the moone:<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> whoſe ſhape in the night it beareth, and is called therefore the Moone-ſtone, &amp;c. It is of a white, blacke, and yellow coullour. His ſcrapings heale the falling ſickneſſe. Bright ſhining Gems doe follow.</p>
               <p>The Carbuncle is a gem ſhining in the light like<note place="margin" type="runSum">Carbuncle.</note> fire: it is the nobleſt, and hath moſt vertues of any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> ſtone.</p>
               <p>The Calcedonian is of a purple coullour, ſhining<note place="margin" type="runSum">Calcedonian. The nature of it.</note> like a ſtarre, it expels ſadnes and feare by purging and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17567:21"/> chearing the ſpirits. It hindreth all viſions.</p>
               <p>The Aſtarites is a Cryſtalline ſtone, having in the<note place="margin" type="runSum">Aſtarites. The nature of it.</note> middeſt like a full moone. Bright ſtones not ſhining do follow: or the leſſe ſhining.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Rubie.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Rubie is a red gemme, ſhining in darke like a ſparke of fire: it cleareth the ſight, it expelleth ſad<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> and fearefull dreames.</p>
               <p>The Topaz is of the colour of gold, caſting<note place="margin" type="runSum">Topaz.</note> beames in the Sunne: being layd to a wound, it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> blood: or caſt into hot water, keepeth the hand from ſcalding.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Hiachinth.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Hiacinth is of wateriſh colour, it is exceeding hard, and cloudie in the darke, but pure and cleare by<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> day. It is colde, moderating the ſpirits of the heart and of the other parts, and cauſing mirth, which being worne obtaineth favour.</p>
               <p>Precious ſtones of leſſe ſhining, be Corrall, Asbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos, Magnes, and Galacte.</p>
               <p>Corall is a ſtone growing in the Sea like a ſlimie<note place="margin" type="runSum">Corrall.</note> ſhrub, which by the ayre preſently is made hard. It is<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> taken up full of moſſe, but being unbarked, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth cleare in his proper colour. The ſpongie Corrall is white and colde. The ſolid is more ſtonie, and is red and blacke. Red and full of branches is the beſt, which worne of one ſhortly to be ſicke, waxeth pale. His tender ſubſtance is affected by the bad vapour, which yet is unable in the body to afflict it. It is good for ſore eyes, for the ſtone, and falling ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>Asbeſtos is of an Iron colour, being once fiered, it<note place="margin" type="runSum">Asbeſtos. The nature of it.</note> cannot be quenched: it is found in Arabia.</p>
               <p>Magnes or Loadſtone is of a skie colour, or an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. The nature of it.</note> colour: It draweth Iron. It hath like vertue
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17567:22"/> with the Adamant. It purgeth the dropſie, belpeth the flux; reſpecteth the North and South pole.</p>
               <p>Galactites is of an Aſh colour, it ſeemeth to ſweat<note place="margin" type="runSum">Galactites. The nature of it.</note> as it were milke, it increaſeth milke, and helpeth run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the eyes, and ulcers.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Now follow ſtones of divers colours.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Achates is a ſtone of divers colours, reſembling a<note place="margin" type="runSum">Achates. The nature of it.</note> Lyons skin: ſometime it is blacke with white veynes and yellow: ſometime it is as it were ſprinkled with bloud, it is very variable in colour. Eagles lay it in their neſts to preſerve their young from poyſon.</p>
               <p>Turcois is darke, of a skie colour, and greeniſh:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Turcois.</note> It helpeth weake eyes and ſpirits.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Corneolus is like water of waſhed fleſh. It helpeth<note place="margin" type="runSum">Corneolus.</note> againſt the Pyles in the fundament, and to ſtop fluxes.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> In a ring it reſtraineth anger.</p>
               <p>Chryſopraſus is of a greene colour with golden<note place="margin" type="runSum">Chryſopraſus.</note> ſpots. It ſhineth a little in the darke, it is rare and deare.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> It comforteth the heart, helpeth dim ſight, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Hematite is of an Iron colour with bloudy veynes:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Hematite.</note> It is cold and dry, cooleth hot waters, ſtancheth bloud,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> and helpeth againſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſcorching of the Sunne, as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors write.</p>
               <p>Alſo the qualities of other ſtones depend rather upon authoritie than upon proofe.</p>
               <p>Stones be found in Beaſts, Birds, and Fiſhes.</p>
               <p>Stones found in Beaſts be;</p>
               <p>1. Chelidonius is a ſmall ſtone in the belly of yong<note place="margin" type="runSum">Chelidonius.</note> Swallowes. It is found in thoſe of the firſt hatching in<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> the new moone: if two be found, the one is red, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blacke. The beſt is of a ſprinkled red. The red in a linnen cloath carried under the left arme, expelleth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17567:22"/> madneſſe, the falling ſickneſſe, and getteth favour, ſay ſome.</p>
               <p>2. Alectorius is of a chriſtall or watriſh colour.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Alectorius.</note> It is found in the Maw of an olde Capon: as big as a beane in one of nine yeere old, ſmall in one of five yeere<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> olde. This ſtone quencheth thirſt, being held in the mouth. It maketh warlike and couragious.</p>
               <p>3. The Rubet or Toadſtone, groweth in the head<note place="margin" type="runSum">Toadſtone.</note> of a Toad: It is of a white browne colour, ſometime<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> it hath a skie coloured eye in the middle: It is to bee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> taken before the Toad touch any Water. It is a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die againſt all poyſon. If it come neare poyſon, it changeth colour, and ſweateth as it were drops.</p>
               <p>In fiſhes are found ſtones which are made of the cold hardening their matter.</p>
               <p>4. The Crabs eye, of the female, is like an eye,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Crabs eye.</note> it diſſolveth bloud congealed, and expelleth<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> ſtones.</p>
               <p>5. The Perch ſtone found in his head, is white and as<note place="margin" type="runSum">Perchſtone,</note> big as Hemp-ſeed.</p>
               <p>6. The Carpe ſtone found in his chap, is triangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Carpeſtone.</note> white without, yellow within. It helpeth againſt<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> aboundance of choller. Thus farre of precious ſtones.</p>
               <p>Theſe following are of price becauſe of their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but not ſo rare.</p>
               <p>Porphirite, is a Marble ſhining like purple. Alaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter<note place="margin" type="runSum">Porphirite. Alabaſter.</note> is a marble like in colour, to ſpotted Honny. At this day it is cleare, and ſmooth, like Plaſter.</p>
               <p>The Ophite is a moſt hard marble, of a ſad greene<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ophite.</note> ſpotted, and ſerpent-like colour.</p>
               <p>Common ſtones are of unpure ſlimie earth, thicke,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Common ſtones.</note>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17567:23"/> and darke: ſome be ſolid, as the Flint, Boulder, the Whet-ſtone, &amp;c. Some be full of pores as the Pumiſe, Gravel-ſtone, and free-ſtone.</p>
               <p>Salt is a fryable mettall, begotten of a wateriſh and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Salt, what it is.</note> earthy moyſture, mixt and decocted together: It<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> bindeth, ſcowreth, purgeth, diſperſeth, repreſſeth, maketh thin and hard. It is gotten in pits or waters. The ſorts of digged ſalts be:</p>
               <p>Salt Amoniack is found in plates under the hotte<note place="margin" type="runSum">Salt Amonaick The nature of it.</note> ſands of Cyreniae. It is hot and dry in the fourth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and ſerveth to purge ſlimie humors. That which Apothecaries ſell in blacke clods, is made of Camels ſtale, and becauſe ſtore of Camels be in Armenia, it is called Armeniack.</p>
               <p>Salt Peter is found in dry places under the ground,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Salt Peter.</note> and in hollow Rockes: It is ſometime called Nitre, of a Region in Egypt. Of this kinde is the ſalt called Borax.</p>
               <p>Salt Gem, is a white kinde of Even-ſalt, ſhining like<note place="margin" type="runSum">Salt Gem.</note> Cryſtall: It is alſo called Stonic, marbly, ſalt Sarma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, or Dacian.</p>
               <p>Salt of Indie is blackiſh Salt, or ruddy. It is in clods<note place="margin" type="runSum">Salt of Indie.</note> cut out of mount Oremen.</p>
               <p>Salt of Water is taken on the Sea coaſt, or from ſome<note place="margin" type="runSum">Salt of water.</note> lakes and ſprings, and it is ſod and congealed of the Sunne, or by fire.</p>
               <p>Allo me is a ſalt ſweat of the earth, it is either liquid<note place="margin" type="runSum">Allome.</note> or hard.</p>
               <p>Liquid Allome is called Roch or Rock-Allome,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Liquid Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome.</note> with it is paper waſhed, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Hard Allome, or Allome Sciſſile is thicke, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Hard Allome.</note> cleaveth: It is as it were gray.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17567:23"/>
               <p>Bitume is a fat and tough moyſture, like pitch, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Bitume.</note> is called Earthy pitch.</p>
               <p>Liquid, is like an oylely moyſture flowing, and is of<note place="margin" type="runSum">Liquid Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tume.</note> divers colours, after the varietie of the place, of which Naphtha is a white fat of Bitumen, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed by water, doth eaſily draw to it fire, through ſtore of oyle that is in it.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Naphtha Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treolum.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Naphtha Petreolum is found in rockes. It is for his fatneſſe of ſome called Oyle.</p>
               <p>Ambar of Arabia is Bitume of an Aſh colour.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ambar of Arabia. Hard Bitume.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Hard Bitume is tough, like foam ſwimming on the water, but being taken forth, it waxeth hard: of this kinde is <hi>Aſphaltus,</hi> which is blacke Bitume, hard like ſtone pitch: The beſt is gotten in the dead Sea of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea. &amp;c.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Piſſaphaltus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Piſſaphaltus Aſphaltus, ſmelling of Pitch, mingled with Bitume: It is called Mummie. Where this wants, they ſell us counterfeit of Syria; for poore men that die there, be ſtuffed with Bitume, but the rich are dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Mirrh, Alloes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It alſo is found in clods rolling from mount Cera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine into the Sea.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Succinum.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Succinum is Bitume, like a ſtone, exceeding hard, named, Ex ſucco, the Iuyce of the earth. It is white or yellow, which is called Ambar, or blacke as Iet. His fatneſſe is ſo great that it burneth like a Candle, and ſmelleth like the Pine tree. It draweth to it chaffe, and ſuch other light ſtuffe, by a certaine hid nature.</p>
               <p>Metallar Earths which are digged forth of mines.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Terra Lemnia</note>
               </p>
               <p>Terra Lemnia, an exceeding red Earth of Lemnos Ile, digged in a red hill: It is ſometime uſed for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menian. In old time this had Dianaes ſeale upon it,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17567:24"/> printed by her Prieſts, who were onely wont to waſh this earth.</p>
               <p>It is of force to expell poyſon, it healeth wounds<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> feſtred and old, and poyſoned.</p>
               <p>Bole Armenian, is earth of Armenia, it is of a pale<note place="margin" type="runSum">Bole Armeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</note> red colour, ſmooth, and eaſie to breake as chalke: It is<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> a dryer, and profiteth againſt all fluxes.</p>
               <p>Terra Samia is white, ſtiffe, and tough, comming<note place="margin" type="runSum">Terra Samia</note> from the Ile Samos.</p>
               <p>Ampelite is a pitchie earth, cleaving and blacke, it<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ampelite.</note> is named of annoynting Vines, to kill the wormes. This earth is like that we call Stone, or Sea coale.</p>
               <p>Chalke is white earth of Creete, and there is found<note place="margin" type="runSum">Chalke.</note> of it in many other places.</p>
               <p>There is alſo ſome found that is blacke, which is<note place="margin" type="runSum">Black Chalke</note> called Pignitis.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Natures perfectly living.</head>
               <p>SO farre of Minerals; Now follow Natures perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly living.<note place="margin" type="runSum">What natures perfectly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving are.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Natures perfectly-living, are Plantes, or bodies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with a ſoule. In all theſe bodies are ſundry vertues, according to the temperature of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall qualities. For the forme uſeth their qualities as Inſtruments: Whence come diverſe diſtinct degrees of thoſe qualities, as ſome are hot, cold, dry, moyſt, in the firſt, ſecond, third, and fourth degree. The qualities in the firſt are obſcure, and ſcarce to be perceived: in the ſecond they are apparant and manifeſt: in the third they be vehement: and in the fourth immoderate, and not to be indured. And againe each of theſe hath a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, middle, and end.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17567:24"/>
               <p>Plants grow from a ſtalke or a trunke. Thoſe from a<note place="margin" type="runSum">Plants.</note> ſtalke have but one ſtalke or many. Trees are Plants having but one ſtalke, full of Boughs, and riſing on high from the earth. Some grow onely in hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: others grow indifferently in all places: thoſe that proſper beſt in hot Regions, are Frankincenſe, Mace, Pepper, Palme, Balſame, Pomegranet, Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Ceder,</p>
               <p>The Frankincenſe tree groweth chiefly in Arabia;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Frankincenſe tree.</note> it is tall, and hath leaves like the Maſtike tree, his gum<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> is ſoft, white, fat, and round, and is apt to perfume, and the ſtiffer and liker Roſen it is, ſo much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This perfume was uſed for ſacrifice.</p>
               <p>Myrrhe is a tree in India, of hard wood, wrythen<note place="margin" type="runSum">Myrrhe.</note> towardes the earth, with a ſmooth barke, the leaves<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> ſharpe poynted towardes the end: his gum is fat, like Roſen, thicke, and ſhining red. The diſtilled liquor of freſh Myrrh was once called Stact, but now it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Storax. It is hot and dry in the ſecond degree. It dryeth &amp; cloſeth wounds, it expelleth the wormes: it is of force againſt an old cough and ſhort winde. It is bitter: It is good to heale wounds of the head.</p>
               <p>Mace is an Indian tree, grown in the Ile of Banda. It<note place="margin" type="runSum">Mace.</note> is almoſt like the Peach tree, it hath narrow and ſhort leaves, whoſe fruit is the Nut-meg covered with Mace.</p>
               <p>The Nut-meg hath an huske like a Filberd: the<note place="margin" type="runSum">Nutmeg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> fruit is covered with a rinde like our Wal-nut, which with ripeneſſe openeth and ſheweth the Mace, which doth cover the Nut-meg, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The new and beſt Nut-meg is full of juyce or oyle, ſmelling ſweete. It dryeth and heateth in the ende of the ſecond degree, with a kindely binding.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pepper,</note>
               </p>
               <p>Pepper groweth in India, Of it be two ſorts of trees,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17567:25"/> and two ſorts of fruits, one long, the other round. The round groweth on branches like vines, which imbraceth trees that ſtand by it; and his fruit is in cluſters, firſt greene, then being dryed, it turneth blacke and rough: it is gathered in October.</p>
               <p>Long Pepper groweth like the long bud on Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> It is hot and dry.</p>
               <p>Palme tree groweth moſt in Egypt, and Arabia, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes<note place="margin" type="runSum">Palme tree.</note> greene, with a long round bodie; his barke is like ſcales of a Fiſh, and the more it is preſſed, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it groweth: therefore was it uſed as a reward for the Conquerour.</p>
               <p>The wild Palme in India, is called Thamarind,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Wilde Palme tree. The nature of it.</note> the Date is his fruit, it being ripe is blacke and ſweete: Of theſe bee three kindes. Our Dates come from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt: they are hot temperately.</p>
               <p>Balſame is a low tree, his trunke is not much unlike<note place="margin" type="runSum">Balſame tree.</note> the Turpentine tree; it hath leaves like Rew, but wither, never falling. It groweth in the valley of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico, and Egypt: being cut it ſendeth out a milkiſh li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor:<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> it is to bee cut in the uper part of the barke with glaſſe or bone, and not with Iron, leaſt it die. His juyce is gathered with wooll into ſmall hornes: of it is ſcarce got each yeare ſix Congies: a Congie is about three Pints.</p>
               <p>Native Balme mixed with milke doth eaſily ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Balme.</note> and eaſily diſſolve in water, neither doth it ſtaine<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> cloth. It is hot and dry in the ſecond degree: it is of thin parts, and hard to come by. In his ſtead moſt commonly is uſed the Oyle of Nut-megges.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17567:25"/>
                     <item>The Pomegranet</item>
                     <item>The Orange</item>
                     <item>The Cedar tree</item>
                  </list> doth follow.</p>
               <p>1. Pomegranet is a low tree, that hath narrow ſhining<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pomegranet.</note> leaves, red flowers, and his fruit filled with graynes. It came from the Country in which Carthage ſtoode;<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> The juyce of this Apple helpeth the ſtomacke: It is very good in a burning Fever.</p>
               <p>2. Pomecytron, Lemmon, and Orange trees,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pomecytron.</note> are alwayes greene, the leafe of the Cytron is like<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> the Lawrell, endented. The fruit is rough, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes fruitfull; his juyce cureth inflammations, and other diſeaſes in the skin: the barke comforteth the heart, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Orange hath a ſmoother skin, and leafe.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Orange.</note>
               </p>
               <p>3. The Cedar is like to Iuniper, his leaves being<note place="margin" type="runSum">Cedar.</note> ſharper: the tree is exceeding tall, chiefly of that of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus;<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> It never rotteth, his nature deſtroying ſound things, preſerveth corrupt things.</p>
               <p>The trees leſſe hot are either fruitfull or barren. The fruitfull have fruit that have a rinde thicke, or thin. The thinner rinde is of Apples, or Berries. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are round, as the Fig, Olive, Plum, Cherry.</p>
               <p>The Fig tree is not high, it hath a ſmooth barke like<note place="margin" type="runSum">Figtree.</note> the Walnut tree. It yeeldeth a long fruit like a Peare, full of graines. It is ſo fruitfull that it bringeth forth three or foure times in a yeare: ſo that one Fig thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth off another. They are of two kindes, great and little.</p>
               <p>The Olive: the Apple tree: and Peach be common.</p>
               <p>The Quince tree is lower then an Apple tree, his<note place="margin" type="runSum">Quince tree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> fruit hath downie hayre; it is called Cidonia, of a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17567:26"/> in Crete, where firſt it grew. The fruit is cold and<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> binding, and doth much profit hot ſtomackes.</p>
               <p>The Peare, the Plum, the Medler, and the Cherry be common.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Now follow thoſe trees that beare Berries.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Lawrell is a tree growing in hotter countryes;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Lawrell tree.</note> which in colde doth hardly proſper; it hath ſharpe and thicke leaves ever greene, with a thin ſmooth barke: His leaves be hot and dry, his oyle for hot and<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> ſoftning nature helpeth diſeaſes of the breſt; and other ſpringing of colde. The powder in wine cauſeth u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, breaketh the ſtone of the bladder and reynes.</p>
               <p>Iuniper beareth a ſmall fruit, the ſpace of two yeares;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Iuniper tree.</note> and before the firſt bee ripe, it bringeth forth other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This tree hath ſhort and ſharpe leaves, and a ſtraight backe, and ſlit almoſt in every place: the gum ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of is, Vernix, called ſo becauſe it congealeth<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> in the ſpring. It is hot and dry in the third degree. It healeth and gleweth, and alſo heateth a colde ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke. His berries are hot and dry in the firſt degree, comforting the ſpirits, and healing putrifactions. It conſumeth rotten and moyſt humors. The oyle hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Gout, if you annoynt the backe-bone there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: it cureth deafeneſſe, and eaten helpeth melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, and ſtayeth the Rheume, and the Flux.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Now follow trees whoſe fruit hath a ſhell.</label>
               </p>
               <p>1. The Almond tree.</p>
               <p>2. The Walnut tree.</p>
               <p>3. The Cheſnut tree taketh his name of a towne<note place="margin" type="runSum">Cheſnut tree.</note> in Magneſia, the tree is much like the Wallnut, yet the leafe hath more veines, and his edge like a Saw. His fruit is covered with a ſharpe huske, and within it hath
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17567:26"/> a red huske. It is of two kindes: both hot and dry in<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> the firſt degree; and for their earthie matter binding. They are hard to diſgeſt, and beget lice: but good if roſted and eaten with Salt, Pepper, and Sugar.</p>
               <p>The powder of dry Cheſnuts voydeth Vrine.</p>
               <p>The Beech is tall with a thicke white barke, or a<note place="margin" type="runSum">Beech tree.</note> ſad red. It hath leaves like Lawrell, nicked on the edge. His fruit is a theerangle Nut, cloſed in a little<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> pricking huske. His fruite is hot, ſweete, and binding. His leaves are coole, which being eaten, doe helpe much the griefe of the gums and lippes. If they bee ſtamped, they much ſtrengthen dead members, being anoynted with it. Swine and Miſe delight much in this fruit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Trees whoſe fruit is but halfe covered.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Oke is a tall tree, having a thicke rough barke,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Oke tree.</note> his leaves are deepe gaſhed, and his boughes are knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: his proper fruit is the Acorne: the gall and his glew are but accidentall. It is moderately hot and dry,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> it bindeth, and eſpecially the little skin which cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Acorne. Diſtilled water of Oke leaves cureth Fluxes, and rottenneſſe of the Liver: and expelleth all congealed bloud. His leaves ſtamped and applyed to greene wounds heale them.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe they draw heate from ſwellings and pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ariſing by heate.</p>
               <p>Galls grow eſpecially in olde Okes, and in the night, in the Summer, the Sunne then leaving Gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni: they bee of two ſorts; ſmall and rough, and great and ſmooth.</p>
               <p>Galls have in them ſometime Spiders, Flies, and Ants: Some thinke Spiders doe preſage peſtilence,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17567:27"/> Flies warre, and Ants dearth. The powder of Galls doth heale wounds without any ſcarre. Robur is very hard and during: It hath leſſe fruit.</p>
               <p>The Ilex is very tall with leaves, Lawrell-like, ever<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ilextree.</note> greene, but leſſer and ſharpe: a thicke wood, and of a blacke red colour; and is very rare.</p>
               <p>Another kinde is the Corke tree, having like leafe,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Corke tree.</note> fruit, and greenneſſe, yet is it leſſer, and hath a moſt thicke barke, which though it bee taken off, yet doth<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> not the tree wither: it is called the female Ilex: his wood is full of pores and holes, and moſt light, and not to be ſunke.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Now follow trees that beare gum, whoſe Nut hath ſcales.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Pine apple is a Tree full of boughes, with hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pine Apple tree.</note> leaves like Combe teeth, of whoſe ſharpe top it takes his name. His fruite is Pine-nuts, theſe are hot<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> and dry, and binde. They are good againſt coughs, and conſumptions, ſtrengthening, and heating.</p>
               <p>The wilde Pine is a great high tree with hairy leaves.</p>
               <p>The Pitch tree is tall with a blacke barke, tough and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pitch tree.</note> ſtiffe, and running along his boughes like a croſſe, from both ſides of the trunke: his leaves are broader, ſofter, and ſmoother than Roſemary. From betweene the barke and wood of this tree floweth a gumme like Rozen.</p>
               <p>The Firre tree is a kinde of Pitch tree, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what<note place="margin" type="runSum">Firre tree.</note> whiter, his leaves on one ſide are of an Aſh co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: from this floweth alſo a Rozen, which ſod with honey profitteth againſt the deſtillations of the head and throat, againſt the Quinſey and other maladies; it aſſwageth the inflammation of woundes, and joyneth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17567:27"/> them: it ſodden with Barley bran and wine, cureth hard kernells.</p>
               <p>The Larix is a high tree with a thicke barke clifted<note place="margin" type="runSum">Larix tree.</note> on each ſide: his boughes grow by degrees about the trunke: his leaves are thicke, long, ſoft, and hairie; his fruit is almoſt like the Cypres, and hath a pleaſant<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> ſmell. The wood of this, for that it is dry and full of Rozen, burneth vehemently, and ſoone melteth met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. His Rozen is in ſmell, taſte, and working better than common Turpentine.</p>
               <p>In colour it is like honey, tough but not hard. In the body of the tree groweth Fungus Agaricus, a ſwamp or muſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rome. The beſt is white, thin, full of pores, light, and eaſie to breake: it purgeth fleame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Now follow trees that bring forth no fruit of note, called Barren-trees.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Elme is tall with rough leaves and ſharpe: his<note place="margin" type="runSum">Elme tree.</note> wood is yellow, hard, &amp; deformed: the barke, boughes,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> and leaves have a healing facultie in ſcabbes. It alſo cloſeth woundes.</p>
               <p>The Alder hath a long ſtraight trunke, his wood is<note place="margin" type="runSum">Alder tree.</note> ſoft, his leafe like Peare-tree, but greater, thicker, and rounder: it groweth in moyſt places, and by rivers. His wood is hot and dry, and indureth long under the<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> earth, or in water. His thin and fat leaves layd upon tumors with hot water cure them, and helpe all ſwellings.</p>
               <p>The Teile is a large and broad tree, with a thicke<note place="margin" type="runSum">Teile tree.</note> ſtalke: his leaves like Ivie, but ſofter and ſharper. It<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> bindeth: his other qualities are like the wilde Olive.</p>
               <p>The Boxe hath little round leaves alwayes greene,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Boxe tree<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> his ſtalke is rough, for moſt part full of knotts, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17567:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:17567:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17567:29"/> blacke: the wood is hard and heavie, it ſinketh in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and never decayeth with age. Of this, boxes are named, becauſe moſt of them were wont to be made of Boxe. It is dry and binding; the powder of his<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> leaves, with Lavender and water, profitteth againſt madneſſe. Lye of Boxe maketh yellow hayres.</p>
               <p>The Birch is a tender tree, his barke is blacke at<note place="margin" type="runSum">Birch tree.</note> firſt, but after white; his wood is ſoft and weake above other. It hath a ſweete ſap; In the rude age, his barke was uſed for paper. His ſap taken in the Spring helpeth<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> the ſtone, Iaundies, and rottenneſſe of the mouth; alſo being put in milke, preſerveth the Cheeſe made of that milke from Maggots.</p>
               <p>Willow groweth apace, it endureth long, for<note place="margin" type="runSum">Willow tree. The nature of it.</note> though it bee hollow and rotten, yet it liveth. It is of two ſorts, ſolid or brittle: the ſolid is blacke or yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: the blacke is the greater and better, and is moſt apt for binding.</p>
               <p>The yellow groweth chiefly neare water, it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time white. The brittle Willow is moſt white, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt for binding. Willowes are dry and thicke: his leaves and barke ſod in Wine, helpeth gripings of the belly.</p>
               <p>The Poplar delighteth in moyſt and watriſh pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Poplar tree.</note> It is white or blacke: the white hath a long ſtraight trunke, and a ſmooth barke: his leafe round, and after ſharper, greene beneath, hoarie above, and do continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſhake; it is moderately hot and dry. The roote taken in drinke, defendeth from gripings in the belly. Blacke Poplar is like the white, but greater, ſofter, and hath narrower leaves, and greene below, and of an<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> Aſh colour above. It is hot and dry: the boughes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17567:29"/> held in the hand (ſome ſay) forbid wearineſſe of hand and foote: his gumme ſtamped helpeth looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Now follow ſhrubs, which ſpring up with many<note place="margin" type="runSum">Shrubs.</note> ſtalkes; and are noble or leſſe noble: The noble, as firſt, Cinnamon, which is a barke of a ſhrub of that<note place="margin" type="runSum">Cinnamon.</note> name growing in India: of a blacke colour, with thin boughes, which if they be broken, caſt forth a ſweete ſent: His barke is of two ſorts, thicke and thinne. The thinne is of the ſharpeſt and beſt taſte. The thicke is more ſlowly digeſted; it comforteth the heart: the beſt<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> is red and ſharpe with ſome ſweetneſſe. It is of ſubtile parts, hot in the third, and dry in the ſecond degree. It helpeth a colde ſtomacke, it ſtrengtheneth the ſight, heart, and liver, and begetteth pure blood.</p>
               <p>Caſſia Fiſtula, is a round, great, and purple Cane,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Caſsia Fiſtula.</note> having a very blacke pith; the heavieſt and reddeſt Canes are beſt. Of the blacke pith is made a good and<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> gentle purgation, called Caſſia extract. This helpeth much againſt feavers, and many other diſeaſes, if one ounce of it be taken with as much Roſe water.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Shrubs leſſe noble.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Haſell is an high ſhrub with a ſlender ſtalke,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Haſell.</note> and full of white ſpots. His leaves are broader, and have more gaſhes than the Alder. The tree beareth the<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> Filberd, and the Nut: theſe Nuts are hot and moyſt, and make fat, but hurt the ſtomacke, and procureth a laske. If ſtamped in water and ſugar, they bee applied, they helpe an old cough. The aſhes burnt with Swines or Boares greaſe, and applyed to the head, cauſeth the hayre to grow.</p>
               <p>The Elderne hath boughes of an Aſh colour, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Elderne.</note>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:17567:30"/> in it is ſtore of pith, and his leaves are much like to thoſe of the Wal-nut tree, it beareth purple berries, having red iuyce.</p>
               <p>Dwarfe Elderne is low &amp; ſhort, with a foure-ſquare ſtalke; theſe plants are hot and dry, and have power to<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> purge and digeſt: Alſo it healeth and cloſeth; the roote or leaves of Elder ſod in wine, purge the dropſie, and nothing is more effectuall to that purpoſe than the roote of Dwarfe Elderne. Water in which the leaves of Elderne are ſod, helpes to rid the dry cough. The Pitch or an electuary of the berries, expelleth ſweate, and all poyſon.</p>
               <p>Barberries are not much unlike the wilde Peare, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though<note place="margin" type="runSum">Barberries.</note> they bee farre leſſe, and in the boughes ſome two or three prickes grow together. His leafe is like<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> Quince leaves, but narrower. Barberries bee hot and dry in the ſecond degree. The iuyce of the berryes profitteth againſt inflammation of the Liver, as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt inward impoſtumes: if it be applyed with night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade, it quencheth thirſt. The barke of his roote or fruit ſtamped, plucketh out a thing faſt in the fleſh: his ſyrrope tempered with ſugar comforteth the hart, reſtoreth appetite, profiteth againſt burning Feavers, and all inward diſeaſes of much blood.</p>
               <p>The ſmall Raiſin hath purple boughes, and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin<note place="margin" type="runSum">Small Rayſin.</note> leaves, but leſſe, and of blackiſh greene: it hath<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> round red berries, upon long ſtalkes; his fruit and leaves are colde and dry in the ſecond degree, having power to cloſe. The iuyce of the fruit taken, helpeth againſt trembling of the heart, &amp; inflammations of the bodie; but chiefly it helpeth the plague: his iuyce with Endive water profitteth to remove ſpecks of the face.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:17567:30"/>
               <p>The Roſe groweth up with ſmall twigs, of a blacke<note place="margin" type="runSum">Roſe.</note> greene, full of crooked prickes; his leaves are dented<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> on the edge; his fruit, namely, Roſes bee of diverſe colours. All Roſes bee colde and dry, and helpe both inward and outward affections of the body.</p>
               <p>The juyce ſod in Wine helpeth griefes of the head, eyes, and gums. Honey and Roſe water ſtrengthen all parts, and purge melancholy and fleame; ſodden with Fennell and Salt, his oyle healeth burnings, and layed on the forehead taketh away heavineſſe, and hot ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. The funge of wilde Roſe trees in powder with wine expelleth the ſtone. Water of Roſes helpeth ſore eyes, comforteth and cooleth the braine, it being drunke, relieveth the heart and ſtomacke: it keepeth the ſpirits, and naturall heate.</p>
               <p>The Bramble is full of prickes, and crawleth about:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Bramble.</note> the leaves of ſweete bryer on the one ſide are white, on the other blacke; his fruite is the blacke berry, full of juyce, the berry is dry, colde, and cloſe. His fruit,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> leaves, or ſprouts quench inward heate. The top of his leaves ſod in Wine ſtay the bloudie flixe, helpe ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the mouth, and faſten looſe teeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poterion, uva oriſpa,</hi> Gooſeberries is full of boughs,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Gooſeberries.</note> hath aſh coloured barke or white, full of ſharpe thornes, his leaves are leſſe than ground Ivie and croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, his berries from greene turne to reddiſh: it is cold<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> in the firſt, dry in the ſecond degree; his greene leaves cure inflammations, and apoſtumes, and aſſwage <hi>Ignis ſacer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Colutea in leafe not unlike to Fengreke, hath a<note place="margin" type="runSum">Colutea.</note> round fruit, as big as a Lentle in a puffed ſhell. It is hot<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> in the beginning of the ſecond degree, and dry in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17567:31"/> firſt: it purgeth the panch: ſcoureth away chiefly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> without trouble, from the head, braine, and the Inſtruments of the ſenſes.</p>
               <p>Thus farre of Plants growing from a trunke or ſtalke, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now follow Herbes which have but a thin ſmall<note place="margin" type="runSum">Herbes.</note> ſtalke, conſiſting moſt upon leaves: Theſe doe nouriſh more or leſſe, as Corne and Pot-herbes, which nouriſh more.</p>
               <p>Wheate is a kinde of Corne, having an eare upon<note place="margin" type="runSum">Wheate.</note> the blade, ſtuffed with many graynes; it is moderately<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> hot and dry, and of much nouriſhment, and helpefull for many diſeaſes, aſwell within as without the body: the beſt is hard to breake, heavie, and of gold colour, ſmooth, and groweth in fat ground.</p>
               <p>Leaven of Wheate doth draw, ripen, and open ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and apoſtumes: Bisket profitteth againſt rheume.</p>
               <p>Barly is cold and dry in the ſecond degree, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Barley.</note> purgeth. His floure and new milke in plaſter cure<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> Biles, and ſuch tumors, by eaſing their paine, and drawing forth heate. Bread made of it begetteth cold and ſlimie humours, and nouriſheth leſſe than wheat, Barley water maketh the skin faire and ſmooth.</p>
               <p>Spelte or Zea is of a middle temperature, betweene<note place="margin" type="runSum">Spelte.</note> Wheate and Barly: it is a kinde of Wheate, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly goeth under that name.</p>
               <p>Rye is not ſo hot as Wheate, and hurteth much, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept<note place="margin" type="runSum">Rye.</note> it be well diſgeſted.</p>
               <p>Oates are colder than Wheate, and of operation al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt<note place="margin" type="runSum">Oates.</note> like Barley.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Now follow of Pulſe:</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Millet.</note>Millet is a moſt fertile Pulſe with ſharpe leaves, broad
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17567:31"/> below, and ſharpe towardes the toppe: his cod hath<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> in it a round long fruit. It is cold in the firſt, and dry in the third degree: It ſtoppeth the belly, and nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth but little.</p>
               <p>Rize is ſmaller than Millet, and farre leſſe, it grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin" type="runSum">Rize.</note> in moyſt and watry places: it bindeth.</p>
               <p>Lentells grow like ſmall peaſe, and have a vertue to<note place="margin" type="runSum">Lentels.</note> binde.</p>
               <p>Peaſe are either of the field or garden; bearing a<note place="margin" type="runSum">Peaſe.</note> white, ot a purple flower.</p>
               <p>Beanes are meanely colde, and moyſt, inflaming,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Beanes.</note> windie, hard to diſgeſt.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Pot herbes.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Now follow Pot-herbes.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Coleworts haue very broad leaves, which encloſing<note place="margin" type="runSum">Colewortes. Their natures.</note> one another round about become Cabbedges. Theſe be colde and moyſt; and in Egypt be very bitter. The Romanes for the ſpace of ſix hundred yeares uſed this onely herbe to cure all diſeaſes. His broath expelleth the ſtone and gravell, his leaves applyed by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or with the flowers cure inflamations: his juyce healeth feſtred ſores, it cureth the falling of the haire. Broath made of his leaves with an olde Cocke, cureth the Collicke, and other gripings.</p>
               <p>Spinagh hath an high ſtalke, and beareth ſharpe<note place="margin" type="runSum">Spinagh.</note> ſeedes, his leaves being ſharpe and triangular; it is<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> colde and moyſt in the firſt degree. His juyce expelleth hurtfull rheume: It mollifieth the belly, and cureth hardneſſe of the backe and belly. His Iuyce taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the paine and heate of the ſtomacke and liver: it helpeth the byting of Spiders,</p>
               <p>Lettiſe hath his leaves gathered into a curled round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Lettiſe.</note> that which groweth in the field hath a ſhorter
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17567:32"/> ſtalke and leafe than Garden Lettiſe, being bitter, and full of milke.</p>
               <p>It is moderately moyſt and colde, like Spring water,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> it is wholſome in Summer, to reſtore appetite to meate. Yet too much of it hurteth the eyes: and boyld with womans milke cureth burnings.</p>
               <p>Beetes have two colours, the one white, the other<note place="margin" type="runSum">Beetes.</note> blacke and red, both of them for their ſalt diſgeſt and cleanſe, but the white is more ſalt, and bindeth, yet being boyled, it looſeneth: It cureth obſtructions of<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> the liver, eſpecially if it be taken with vineger and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard: It alſo cureth thoſe that be ſicke of the ſplene.</p>
               <p>Purſlaine hath round, thicke, fat, and white leaves<note place="margin" type="runSum">Purſlaine:</note> on the backe, a red ſtalke, yellow flowers like a Starre: They of the Garden have broad leaves, and a thicke ſtalke: the wilde, leſſer, and more leaves. It is colde in<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> the firſt, and moyſt in the ſecond degree: it is tart; his juyce helpeth a hot ſtomacke, and hot diſeaſes; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat binding, helpeth fluxes, and evacuations of bloud, if it be uſed with Barly flower.</p>
               <p>Garden Mallowes grow with a round leafe, and high<note place="margin" type="runSum">Mallowes.</note> ſtalke, his flowers be red, or white: wilde Mallowes mollifie, and a little diſgeſt: Garden, are moyſt, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> weaker. The decoction of Mallowes drunke, cureth on old cough: his leaves ſod and uſed with common oyle heale burning.</p>
               <p>The Onion hath a ſubtile ſtalke, round and hollow,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Onion.</note> ariſing from a round roote, wound about with many fouldings: it is hot almoſt in the fourth degree: it is<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> of thicke partes: his juyce is a dry ſubſtance, and hot. An Onion all night layd in cold water and drunke, killeth wormes, and being beaten with ſalt, it draweth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17567:32"/> away warts by the rootes: his juyce put in the eare cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth deafeneſſe.</p>
               <p>The Leeke groweth almoſt like Onions, and is of<note place="margin" type="runSum">Leekes.</note> the ſame qualitie, it doth diſſolve ſwellings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> bloud, being applyed like a Plaſter.</p>
               <p>Parſley hath leaves like Cicuta, it is hot and dry in<note place="margin" type="runSum">Parſley.</note> the third degree, it peirceth and diſſolueth, provoking<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> urine; the ſeede is more effectuall than the herbe. It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth the ſtone, it conſumeth ill moyſture, and ſores of the head.</p>
               <p>Theſe hearbes following are uſed for Garlands, or phyſicke; ſome of them ſmelling ſweetly.</p>
               <p>The Violet hath leaves leſſer and thinner than I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Violet.</note> but more blacke; his ſtalke commeth from the midſt of his roote, beareth a purple flower, and a ſeed full of graynes. It ſpringeth in woods, and ſhadowie<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> places, wilde, but not ſweete: it is cold in the firſt, and moyſt in the ſecond: and cooleth hot diſeaſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammations. Of it there be divers kindes, and colours: as the Pancey or Harts-eaſe.</p>
               <p>The Daiſie hath leaves ſomewhat round above and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Dayſie. The nature of it.</note> ſmall below, and the roote in the ground wheeling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: it is cold in the ſecond degree.</p>
               <p>The Ielly-flower hath ſharpe leaves, growing like<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ielly-Flower.</note> graſſe with flowers of ſundry colours: it hath an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> force, and the juyce healeth wounds in the head.</p>
               <p>Maioram hath almoſt a woodden ſtalke, with many<note place="margin" type="runSum">Maioram. The nature of it.</note> rough round leaves, and it ſmelleth ſweetly. It is hot and dry in the fourth degree, it is of thin parts, and of a diſgeſting facultie. It healeth, diſgeſteth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh vrine.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:17567:33"/>
               <p>Roſemary is hot and dry in the third degree, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Roſemary.</note> ſmelleth like Frankincenſe. It mollifieth, diſgeſteth,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> and dryeth.</p>
               <p>Spicknard is hot in the firſt, and dry in the ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Spicknard.</note> 
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Lavender heateth and dryeth in the ſecond degree.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Lavender.</note>
               </p>
               <p>White Daffodill is hot and dry. It is of diverſe<note place="margin" type="runSum">Daffodill.</note> kindes.</p>
               <p>Roſe Campion is an hearbe with an Aſh coloured<note place="margin" type="runSum">Roſe Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> ſtalke, as it were cotton, long leaved, and white, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purple flowers, growing up like the Prim-roſe:<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> his ſeede is hot and dry almoſt in the ſecond degree: it prevaileth againſt the ſtinging of Scorpions.</p>
               <p>Herbes uſed in medicine, are Aromatike, or ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Aromaticke doe comfort and ſtrengthen the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Thence they take their name.</p>
               <p>Saffron is hot in the ſecond, and dry in the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Saffron.</note> it a little bindeth, and concocteth; it may with good keeping be preſerved five yeares.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It comforteth the heart and ſtomacke, it maketh pure bloud, and provoketh vrine, it ſcowreth the breſt, it is deadly, if it be taken too much.</p>
               <p>Ginger waxeth greene twiſe or thriſe in the yeare,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ginger.</note> it heateth in the third, and is moyſt in the firſt, it is of<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> more ſubtile parts than Pepper.</p>
               <p>Zadury or Wormeſeede heateth and dryeth in the<note place="margin" type="runSum">Wormeſeede.</note> ſecond degree, it is that we doe call the roote of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, like Ginger but not ſo biting.<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Gallingall is the roote of a plant growing in Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis<note place="margin" type="runSum">Gallingall.</note> and Syria, it groweth like the flouredeluce, but with prickes, and is broader and thicker from the<note place="margin" type="runSum">The nature of it.</note> roote. It is hot and dry in the third degree, as is the roote of Cyprus.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17567:33"/>
               <p>Calamus Aromaticus is an hearbe of India, growing<note place="margin" type="runSum">Calamus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romaticus. The nature of it.</note> like reeds or figs. It is hot and dry in the ſecond degree, and a little binding.</p>
               <p>Acorus is a plant growing with leaves like Iris, but<note place="margin" type="runSum">A corus. The nature of it.</note> ſmaller, or like ſegges; the roote is white, ſweetly ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. It is hot and dry in the ſecond degree.</p>
               <p>There be ſexes of hearbes, as of other living things, ſome of which more helpe, namely, the Male or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male according to their kindes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of humane Creatures.</head>
               <p>MAn is a creature that hath reaſon, &amp; as he is moſt<note place="margin" type="runSum">What man it, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</note> excellent, ſo hath he a more perfect ſhape in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy than others. His members are formed, and beginne to appeare diſtinctly about the ſix and twentieth day. And they are all perfect in Males at thirty dayes, and in Females at 36. dayes. About this time the Childe beginneth to live, and to feele. The Male is moved in the third Month, but the Female in the fourth Month: then it is nouriſhed and increaſed till the ninth Month, and after the ninth Month, when it is growne great, it is brought forth. This is the forming, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creating of Man, for whoſe ſake all other creatures were made.</p>
               <p>A feeling ſoule is a power apprehending and<note place="margin" type="runSum">What a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſoule is.</note> perceiving things placed without the body of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creatures. This facultie is exerciſed by the ſences, and by motion accompanying the ſences. The ſences are outward or inward. The outward onely<note place="margin" type="runSum">Sences out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> perceiving things preſent: And every one of theſe have
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17567:34"/> their proper ſubject: and the moſt have a middle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument; of all which, if there bee a certaine mutuall conſent and juſt proportion: the ſences become of more force: but if any one of them have too excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent an object, or his inſtrument bee corrupt, they are dull and unfit to be uſed; This is the cauſe of blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to thoſe that walke in ſnow, and of deafeneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Smithes, &amp;c. Furthermore, ſences are common to the whole body, or proper to ſome part thereof. The<note place="margin" type="runSum">Touching.</note> ſence in the whole body is touching. This is a ſence by meanes of fleſh, full of ſinewes, apprehending tactill qualities.</p>
               <p>His inſtrument is fleſh, full of ſinewes, or rather a nerve like a hayre diſperſed throughout the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. In man for the abundance of nerves is this ſence moſt quicke; his meanes is fleſh and skin, for though the skinne be removed, yet a man feeleth hurt. Sences of certaine parts are more or leſſe noble. The nobler are Seeing, and Hearing; whoſe meanes are the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Geeing.</note> and ayre: Sight by the eye perceiveth bright and coloured things: The ſubject thereof is light, &amp;c. Greene a moſt temperate colour is moſt acceptable to the ſight. His inſtrument is the nerve Opticke, which from the braine commeth to the eyes.</p>
               <p>Hearing is a ſence perceiving ſoundes; his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin" type="runSum">Hearing.</note> is a little skin in the loweſt winding, or turning of the eare, dry and full of holes: the skin is double, one below, which covereth a little bone like an Anvile: another above, containing a little bone, as it were a ſmall Mallet. The upper ſtriken by the ſoundes, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the lower, and ſtirreth up the ſpirits in the nerves to perceive the ſound.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:17567:34"/>
               <p>The more un-noble ſences are Taſting, and Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Taſting.</note> Taſting apprehendeth taſtes. His inſtrument is a nerve ſtretched like a Net upon the fleſh of the tong, which is full of little pores. His meanes is a temperate ſalt humour, which if it doe exceed the juſt quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, it doth not exactly perceive taſtes: but if it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together conſumed, no taſtes are perceived.</p>
               <p>Smelling judgeth qualities fit for ſmell: his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin" type="runSum">Smelling.</note> is the entrance into the firſt ventricle covered with a ſmall skin; the dryer it is the quicker of ſmell, as in Dogs and Vultures: but man for the moyſtnoſſe of his braine, hath but a dull ſmell.</p>
               <p>Now follow the inward ſences, which beſide things<note place="margin" type="runSum">Sences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> preſently offered, doe know formes of many abſent things. By theſe the creature doth not onely perceive, but alſo underſtandeth that which hee doth perceive. Theſe have their ſeate in the braine: They are either conceiving or preſerving: Conceiving exerciſeth his<note place="margin" type="runSum">Conceiving.</note> facultie by diſcerning, or more fully judging: it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Common ſence, and the other is Phantaſie. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence more fully diſtinguiſheth ſenſible things; his inſtrument is the former ventricle of the braine, made by dryneſſe ſit to receive. Phantaſie is an inward ſence more diligently examining the forms of things: This is the thought and judgement of creatures, his place is the middle part of the braine, being through dryneſſe apt to retaine.</p>
               <p>The preſerving ſence is Memory, which according<note place="margin" type="runSum">Preſerving.</note> to the conſtitution of the braine is better or worſe. It is weaker in a moyſt braine than in the dry braine. His inſtrument is the hinder part of the braine.</p>
               <p>Memorie calling backe images preſerved in former
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17567:35"/> time, is called Remembrance: but this is not without the uſe of reaſon, and therefore is onely attributed to man.</p>
               <p>The wittie excell in remembrance, the dull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie.</p>
               <p>Sleepe is the reſting of the feeling facultie: his cauſe<note place="margin" type="runSum">Sleepe how cauſed.</note> is a cooling of the brayne by a pleaſant abounding va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, breathing forth of the ſtomacke, and aſcending to the braine. When that vapour is concoct, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin" type="runSum">Waking how cauſed.</note> into ſpirits, the heate returneth, and the ſences re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering their former function, cauſe waking. There be certaine appointed courſes for watch and ſleepe, loſt creatures languiſh with overmuch motion.</p>
               <p>Affections of ſleepe are Dreames, Night-mare, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Dreames<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Extaſie, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>A dreame is an inward act of the minde, the bodie<note place="margin" type="runSum">What they be.</note> ſleeping: and the quieter that ſleepe is, the eaſier bee dreames: but if ſleepe bee unquiet, then the minde is troubled.</p>
               <p>Varietie of dreames is according to the divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution<note place="margin" type="runSum">Their variety.</note> of the body.</p>
               <p>The cleare and pleaſant dreames are when the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the braine, which the ſoule uſeth to imagine with, are moſt pure and thin, as towardes morning when concoction is perfected.</p>
               <p>But troubleſome dreames are when the ſpirits bee thicke and unpure. All naturall dreames are by ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, either before proffered to memorie, or conceived by temperature alone, or by ſome influence from the ſtarres, as ſome thinke.</p>
               <p>From dreames many things may be collected, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the conſtitution of the body.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:17567:35"/>
               <p>The Night-mare, is a ſeeming of being choked or<note place="margin" type="runSum">The night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare.</note> ſtrangled by one leaping upon him: feare following this compreſſion, the voyce is taken away. This af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection<note place="margin" type="runSum">How occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</note> commeth when the vitall ſpirits in the braine are darkened by vapours, aſcending from melancholy and phlegme, inſomuch, that that facultie being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſome heavie thing ſeemeth to bee layd upon us.</p>
               <p>Therefore this diſeaſe is familiar to thoſe, who through age or ſexe are much inclined unto theſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
               <p>An Extaſie or traunce, is a vehement imagination<note place="margin" type="runSum">A trance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> of the departure (for a time) of the ſoule from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. A deepe ſleepe laſting ſome dayes enſeweth, for<note place="margin" type="runSum">What it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> the foule giving over it ſelfe to cogitation, ceaſeth to ſerve the body. Wherefore men wanting motion and ſence ſeeme to be dead. And with what humours the braine ſhall be compaſſed, ſuch phanſies doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, although ſometime ſpirits working on ſuch phataſies, imprint other things.</p>
               <p>Now followeth Motion, which accompanieth ſence, and is cauſed either by appetite, or change of place; for we deſiring things perceived in ſence, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attaine unto them withour moving our body to that thing.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Appetite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What it is.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Appetite is a facultie deſiring ſuch things as are objects to our ſenſe. It chiefly followeth touching, or thinking. Delight followeth touching. Delight is a deſire of an agreeing Object. Griefe is his contrary, which is a turning from the hurtfull object, or from that we count unpleaſant. Appetites following cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, are all the motions of the heart, which be called
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17567:36"/> affections, and are either good or bad. The good cheriſh and preſerve the nature of our ſenſitive facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as mirth, love, hope, which come of heate: when the heart dilating it ſelfe, deſireth to enjoy the thing, with which it is delighted.</p>
               <p>Motion is a facultie of living creatures, ſtirring a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Motion what it is.</note> entiſed by appetite from one place to another. It is either of the whole body, or of partes: Of the whole body, as by going, &amp;c. Of partes, as breathing, which is made either by enlarging of the parts, which ſerve for the taking in of the ayre, or by the cloſing of them for the expelling of corrupt ayre.</p>
               <p>Now followeth to intreat, Of the bodies of living<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of the bodies of living creatures. What the matter of the body is.</note> creatures.</p>
               <p>The matter of the body in which the foreſaid fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties be, is the ſeede of both ſexes. Seede is moſt pure bloud, perfectly concocted in the teſticles, and it is gathered from the whole bodie. For the teſticles lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king nouriſhment, draw bloud from the hollow veyne and change it.</p>
               <p>Conception is the action of the wombe, by which<note place="margin" type="runSum">Conception, what it is.</note> the power is ſtirred up to execute his inbred gift. Then that power being ſtirred up doth diverſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract the matter, ſeparating his divers partes: and thus all parts alike get together their ſhape. Likewiſe all of them together are adorned with the faculties of the vegetative, or ſenſitive ſoule. Amongſt the naturall faculties of the partes of the body, if there be putrifac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a fault of the concocting facultie, there is made a certaine generation of matter: This is naturall, or extraordinary.</p>
               <p>Naturall is by an inbred heate, not altogether ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Naturall.</note>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:17567:36"/> but ſlackly exerciſing force, through diſpoſition of the mattter. Such is to be ſeene in inflamations, bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and impoſtumes. For in theſe, nature ſo farre as it can, laboureth to bring this his ſubject matter to the beſt forme. Therefore ſuch ſuppuration is wont to argue a certaine ſtrength of nature, wherefore often with convenient helpes, it is carefully encreaſed. In this kinde, eſpecially is prayſed white, thicke, ſmooth, equall, and leaſt ſmelling matter.</p>
               <p>Extraordinary mattering is, when nature altogether<note place="margin" type="runSum">Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> ſubdued, the humors or parts themſelves are made full of corrupt matter through ſtore of rottenneſſe.</p>
               <p>But nature, or the concocting facultie, is overcome either through proper weakneſſe, or by corrupt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: this is obſerved in all rotten, malignant, and ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king botches, in which according to the diverſe faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning of abounding matter, are found diverſe ſorts of ſolid bodyes, as haires, and ſuch other like.</p>
               <p>Of partes of the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> body which appertaine to the<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of the parts of the body.</note> making up of the whole body, ſome are containing, and ſome contained. The contained for their fluent nature are ſuſtained by helpe of others: Such are hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and ſpirits. Humors are moyſt partes begot of the firſt mixture of nouriſhment in the liver. Theſe are in the ſeede of creatures, and are called the beginning of things endued with bloud. Any of theſe if they fayle of their proper nature, are not fit to be in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but are become unnaturall.</p>
               <p>Humours are of the firſt, &amp; the ſecond ſort. The firſt<note place="margin" type="runSum">Humors.</note> are hot or colde, and moyſt, and dry: Bloud is hot and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Blood.</note> moyſt, and it is a thin, red, humour, and ſweete. With this the other partes be chiefly nouriſhed, amongſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17567:37"/> whom this is the chiefe. The faults of this is in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as putrifaction, or mixture of vicious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: or in qualitie, as too thicke or too thin; or is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with ſome other badneſſe. The humour that is hot and dry, is choller; this is a thinne, yellow, pale, and bitter humour. His uſe is to helpe the expelling facultie, and chiefly in the Guts. Gall beſides nature, through aduſtion is yellow, like an egges yolke, in the ſtomacke it is like ruſtic braſſe.</p>
               <p>The colde and moyſt is phlegme, which is a tough,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Phlegme.</note> ſlimie, and whitiſh humour, and taſtleſſe. If this have a fuller concoction, it is turned into bloud. His uſe is to moyſten the joynts. When it declineth from his proper nature, it is ſalt or tart, according to his mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The colde and dry humour is blacke choller. This is a thicke, blackiſh, tart, bitter humour. It ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to ſtrengthen the ſtomacke, that it may more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily retaine, and receive meate. When it declineth from his proper nature by immoderate burning, it hath divers kindes. Humors of the ſecond ſort are begotten of the firſt, being wrought with concoction they are like dew or glew. Dew is a humor contained in the hollowneſſe of the members, and joyned to their ſubſtance, like dew, with which they are nouriſhed.</p>
               <p>Glew is a humour immoderately congealed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin" type="runSum">Glew.</note> firmely faſtned to the members, beginneth to bee changed unto their ſubſtance, of which change it is called <hi>Cambium,</hi> and <hi>carniformis,</hi> like the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Now follow the ſpirits, which are a fluent part of<note place="margin" type="runSum">Spirits.</note> the body, moſt thin, and begotten of the bloud of the heart. The ſpirits are the chiefe inſtrument, and as it were the Chariot of the ſoules faculties, for with moſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17567:37"/> ſpeedie, and ſwift motion, it carrieth them over all the body.</p>
               <p>Spirits having roote in the heart, be either abſolute<note place="margin" type="runSum">Vitall. What they are.</note> or rude, and to be finiſhed in other parts. Vitall ſpirits be abſolute in the heart, and are of a firie nature, and from the heart by arteries are ſpred in the bodie, by whoſe communication all parts doe live.</p>
               <p>Spirits to be perfected in other parts bee Animall,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Animall.</note> which from the heart be carried into the braine, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">What they are.</note> there made ſubtile by nerves, flowing unto all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts; and this is the Chariot of functions or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of all living Creatures.</p>
               <p>Parts containing are more ſolid, which are ſuſtained by themſelves; all theſe either are as a ſtay or covering. The ſtay to other parts, is either bone, or griſtle. Bone is the hardeſt and dryeſt part, and ſtay to all the bodie. Bones are knit together by ligaments, which are like hard and thicke threeds, being as bandes to the bones of the bodie.</p>
               <p>Griſtles are ſomewhat ſofter than the bones, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Griſtles.</note> ſuſtaine all other partes. The covering of the other<note place="margin" type="runSum">What they are.</note> parts, is the skin, which is tender without bloud, and covereth the whole body. The membrane is a tender skin, covering ſome parts.</p>
               <p>There is yet in theſe parts a common excrement of<note place="margin" type="runSum">Sweat.</note> concoction, which is ſweat, and is a moyſtneſſe of the<note place="margin" type="runSum">What it is,</note> veynes, expelled by ſecret pores; of this is to be ſeene a diverſe colour, according to the die of the moyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or matter thereof: the uſuall is watriſh, through the white ſubſtance of the channels, through which it runneth. But if the pores be large and open, that without delay, and long change it may ſlide through
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17567:38"/> them: eſpecially, if for ſome affection of minde or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, it become thinner, then is it ſpeedily expelled, and tainted with ſome other colour, &amp;c. Therefore from the colour of ſweate, the bodyes conſtitution may be knowne. Colde ſweate is worſe to bee liked than hot, but either is bad if they be unequall.</p>
               <p>Alſo the containing parts afore-named are animall, or vitall, and each of theſe are more, or leſſe principall. Animall parts are, in which the animall parts are moſt exerciſed, as ſence and motion together, or alone. The chiefe member of motion and ſence, is the braine contained in the head; whoſe ſubſtance being hurt, it is in danger to loſe both ſence and motion.</p>
               <p>The Braine is ſofter than the other parts, white,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Braine, what it is.</note> and covered with a double skinne cloſely. The skinne of the brayne is either called <hi>Pia,</hi> or <hi>Dura mater.</hi> The ſcalpe is a thicke bone, covering the whole head, and hath up on it a skin with hayres. The ſcalpe is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed with certaine ſeames in certaine parts, which are true or fayned, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The excrements of the braine are either thicke or<note place="margin" type="runSum">Excrements of the braine.</note> thin: The thin are teares burſting from the braine by the angles of the eyes. The greater the fleſh of thoſe angles be, ſo much more plentifull be teares, chiefly if the complexion bee colde and moyſt, as of women. Teares be cauſed by heate which openeth, or colde which preſſeth the fleſh, and cauſeth teares.</p>
               <p>The thicker excrements which are expelled from the brayne, eyther are by the eares or noſe.</p>
               <p>In the eares is a moyſt excrement of the brayne, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of the eares.</note> and rotting in their hollowneſſe.</p>
               <p>That of the noſe is a thicker excrement than that of<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of the noſe.</note>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:17567:38"/> the braine: which although it be like flegme, yet it is altogether of another nature. The pithe of the backe bone is neare to the nature of the braines excrement, ſave that it is harder and ſomething hotter. The backe is bonie, round, and in his length hath twentie foure joynts. The Nerves are leſſe principall parts of ſence and motion, which if they be out of order, the parts in which theſe be, become unfit to move. Nerves or ſinewes are thin parts, round, &amp;c. white, much like to thicke threeds. Some are ſofter, ſome harder. The ſofter are of more uſe, of which are ſix paire, by two and two, from the braine arriving to other parts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to the eyes. Secondly, To moove the eyes. Thirdly, to the tongue and taſte. Fourthly, to the pallet and skin of the mouth. Fiftly, to the hearing. The ſixt, to the mouth of the ſtomacke, by which ſence and motion deſcend.</p>
               <p>Hard Nerves have a duller facultie, and leſſe ſerving to the ſenſes, of which are thirtie paire, which by couples come from the marrow of the backe bone: by whoſe conduct the backe eaſily executeth his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Of the parts to breath.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The principall parts of breathing are in the breſt:<note place="margin" type="runSum">The breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts.</note> being either Lightes or Heart; wherefore theſe being touched, breathing is immediately hurt, and ſuch wounds be deadly. The Longes are a ſpongious and thin part, ſoft, and like foame of congealed bloud, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining ſomething to the right ſide. Breath is brought unto the Lightes by a rough Artery, knit to the roote of the tongue. This Arterie is a long channell made of many griſtle rings on a row, which endeth in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17567:39"/> Lights. If any thing fall into the hollowneſſe of this, the breath is hindred, and there is danger to be choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
               <p>The Heart is a fleſhie part, ſolid, and well compac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin" type="runSum">The heart, what it is.</note> almoſt like a Pyramis: it hath two ventricles, the right and the left. The right by an arteriall veine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth bloud to the Lights. This veine is ſo called of a proper ſubſtance and office. From the left ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Heart ariſeth Aorta the roote of all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries. Theſe are hollow veſſells in the Heart begotte: and are thicke, diſtributing ſpirits throughout the whole bodie.</p>
               <p>The excrements of the principall parts of breathing<note place="margin" type="runSum">Spittle, what it is.</note> be ſpittle and cough. Spittle is a windie foame caſt out of the breſt, and his parts: If it be avoyded with noyſe, it is called coughing. Superfluitie of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is judged by the colour, for red ſpittle is of bloud, yellow of choler: white of flegme, and blacke of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy:</p>
               <p>The leſſe principall parts of breathing, are the<note place="margin" type="runSum">Midriffe, what it is.</note> midriffe, and the mediaſtin. The midriffe is a thinne skin, like perchment, faſtened overthwart to the ſides, and includeth the parts of the breſt, The mediaſtin is a double skinne in length, dividing the breſt into two ſides.</p>
               <p>The vitall parts are thoſe which ſerve to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the ſpirits of living creatures, and are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to nouriſhment, or generation. The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall parts for the perfection of nouriſhment be the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and the Liver.</p>
               <p>The Stomacke is a part like perchment, ſticking to<note place="margin" type="runSum">Stomacke, what it is.</note> the throat, round, but long, and as it were, twiſted
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17567:39"/> with many ſmall threeds, and it is the kitchin of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment to be concocted.</p>
               <p>The throat is a channell, full of nerves, carrying<note place="margin" type="runSum">Throat, what it is.</note> meate from the mouth to the ſtomacke. The Fibres are as it were, very ſmall threeds, by benefit whereof the ſtomacke enjoyeth her facultie. Theſe if they bee ſtraight and right, draw nouriſhment unto them: if crooked, they are oblique or tranſverſe: thoſe retaine nouriſhment received; theſe expell excrements.</p>
               <p>The caſting forth of excrements by the upper parts<note place="margin" type="runSum">Vomiting.</note> of the ſtomacke, is called vomit, which expelleth that which aboundeth in the ſtomacke: yet ſuch excrement is many times ſent backe from other parts into the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke. The Liver lyeth upon the ſtomacke on the<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Liver.</note> right ſide, encloſing it with his laps, and is a fleſhy part of nouriſhment, red, like congealed bloud, placed next unto the Midriffe. In the Liver is made the ſecond concoction, namely, of nouriſhment in the belly, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a red maſſe: from the Liver ariſeth a hollow veine, the roote of all other veynes. Theſe are hollow parts, round, and guide the bloud unto all the body; the ſubſtance of theſe is thinner by ſixe folde than the skin of the Arteries, whoſe ſubſtance ought to be thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker for the vehement motion of the ſpirits. That the office of the Liver may be made perfect by meanes of veynes, other particles are allotted thereunto: which receive the abounding humors, choller, &amp;c. The Gall receiveth yellow choller, and the Milt blacke. The bladder of the Gall is a ſlimie part in the hollow part of the Liver, of the figure of a Peare: the Milt is a long part like a ſhooe-ſole, on the left ſide over againſt the Liver, but ſomewhat lower. Water from the Liver is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17567:40"/> received by the reines and bladder. The ſubſtance of the reines is thicke, and ſolid fleſh; they ſticke on both ſides about the loynes, and have emulgent veynes ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the hollow veine. From the trench of the veynes hang downeward white, narrow veynes, guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water from the reines unto the bladder. The blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is a ſlimie part, round, and containing urine in it. Vrine is a whey ſeparated from bloud in the reines,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Vrine.</note> and more fully purged in the bladder. This in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of a temperate man, and ſound, is of a meane ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and in quantitie anſwereth the drinke recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: in the chollerike it is yellow, or red. His ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment is white, ſmooth, and equall without bubbles, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>A ſound body is knowne by voyding vrine, which<note place="margin" type="runSum">How to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne a ſound body by it.</note> in the morning is white, and after ſomething red. For the one ſignifieth that it doth, and the other that it hath concocted. Vrine is of a meane ſubſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thin and thicke. Thin vrine argueth the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the body, and coldneſſe predominant, and rawneſſe of the parts of concoction. And this either remaineth the ſame or becommeth troubled. That ſheweth concoction is not yet begunne, and therefore raw, or This, that it is but new begunne. Thicke vrine like that of beaſts, noteth exceſſe of matter or concoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Vrine doth varie according to age or complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or according to dyet and affections of the minde. For the vrine of Infants for the moſt part is white and milkie, the vrine of boyes is thicker, and not ſo white, the vrine of young men is like golde, and of olde men white and thin.</p>
               <p>Touching complexions, the chollerick have Orange<note place="margin" type="runSum">Complexions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:17567:40"/> colour: Phlegmatike pale, and thicke: the Sanguine, red and meane. The melancholike, wan and thin.</p>
               <p>Dyet changeth vrine, as Saffron or Caſſia cauſſth O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range<note place="margin" type="runSum">Dyet.</note> colour. Vrine of thoſe that faſt long is yellow, of thoſe that eate too much, it is white.</p>
               <p>The leſſe principall parts of concoction, are the<note place="margin" type="runSum">Guts.</note> gutts and meſenterion. The gutts are long, round, hollow, and are knit to the lower part of the ſtomacke. Theſe are thicke or thin. The thinner are the three uppermoſt, as <hi>Duodenum, Iejunum,</hi> and <hi>Ileos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Duodenum</hi> is the uppermoſt gut, twelue fingers long.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Their ſeverall kinds.</note> The <hi>Iejunum</hi> beginneth where the <hi>Duodenum</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to turne unto rundells. <hi>Ileos</hi> is a thin gut, having inwrapped windings. The thicker guts of a thicker skin, are <hi>Coecum, Colon,</hi> and <hi>Rectum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The blinde gut is thicke, large, and ſhort, having but one mouth. The <hi>Colon</hi> hath many turnings. The right goeth ſtraight to the <hi>Tuell:</hi> The excrement of the belly, if it be but ſoftly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> compact, and made at the appointed time, and ſomewhat yellow, and not much ſmelling, argueth good concoction. If it be red, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth, that much colour floweth in the ſtomacke: if it be white, it ſheweth cruditie and want of choller.</p>
               <p>Blew ſheweth mortification, and cold of the inward parts. Too thicke or thin egeſtion, argueth bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction: if fattiſh, or ſlimie, it noteth a conſumption. Above all, in theſe things it muſt bee obſerved, what meate hath lately beene received.</p>
               <p>The guts are wrapped about with the Meſenterion,<note place="margin" type="runSum">How placed in the body.</note> which is a skin in the end full of kernells, and woven with many thin veines, which meeting together, make a multiplying of <hi>Vena porta</hi> in the hollow of the Liver.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:17567:41"/>
               <p>Thus of the common parts of all creatures: their kindes follow.</p>
               <p>All Creatures are reaſonable, or unreaſonable. They<note place="margin" type="runSum">The diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of living creatures, and their ſeverall kinds.</note> which want reaſon, are Beaſts, who live on Land or in Water. Thoſe which live on the earth, moove on the earth, or in the ayre. Beaſts moving on the earth, are fourefooted, or creeping. Fourefooted Beaſts, bring forth young ſhaped as themſelves, or eggs. Thoſe that bring forth living Creatures, ſome have ſolide feete, and ſome cloven feete. They have ſolide feete who want hornes, as Horſes, Mules, and Aſſes, &amp;c. The cloven footed Beaſtes, for the moſt part have hornes, as the Oxe, Goate, Hart, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Land Beaſts bringing forth eggs, are the Crocodiles, and ſome which have a ſhell.</p>
               <p>Frogges, Liſerts, and ſome Serpents have foure feete.</p>
               <p>Creatures creeping on the earth, are all kinde of Wormes, Ants; Earwigs: to whom may bee added, Spiders, Lice, Gnatts, and ſuch other.</p>
               <p>Fowles are hotter and dryer than Creatures living onely on the land, and all of them bring forth egges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and have but two feete. They have either whole feete or clawes. Geeſe, Duckes, Swannes, have whole feete to rowe in the water.</p>
               <p>Other Birds for the moſt part have clawes, as Doves, Swallowes, Hennes, Sparrowes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The inſect of Fowles, are Waſpes, Bees, Hornetts, Gnatts, Flies. Theſe Creatures are they which live upon the earth: thoſe that live in the water, are Fiſhes, or of that kinde, as the Sea-Horſe, the Sea-Dog, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fiſhes many of them are like to Creatures living on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17567:41"/> the earth in their parts: but they have not ſo much bloud: therefore they are colder and moyſter.</p>
               <p>Fiſhes are ſoft, or hard: the ſoft have ſcales, or one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a skin.</p>
               <p>Of the ſcalie be the Carpe, the Pearch. Of the ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie be Eeles.</p>
               <p>The harder fiſhes have plates, as the Crabbe, the Lobſter, &amp;c. Or ſhells, as Oyſters, Muſſells, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
